<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue, concerning the strife of our churche wherein are aunswered diuers of those vniust accusations, wherewith the godly preachers and professors of the Gospell, are falsly charged; with a briefe declaration of some such monstrous abuses, as our byshops haue not bene ashamed to foster.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20391</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6801</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109629</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845276</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845276</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10166</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20391)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10166)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 420:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue, concerning the strife of our churche wherein are aunswered diuers of those vniust accusations, wherewith the godly preachers and professors of the Gospell, are falsly charged; with a briefe declaration of some such monstrous abuses, as our byshops haue not bene ashamed to foster.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 136 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Walde-graue,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark.</note>
                  <note>Quire K is in two settings; K3r has catchword (1) "God" or (2) "God?".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Puritans --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10166:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10166:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A DIALOGVE,</hi> CONCERNING <hi>the ſtrife of our Churche: <hi>Wherein are aunſwered diuers of thoſe</hi>
               </hi> vniuſt accuſations, wherewith the godly <hi>preachers and profeſſors of the Goſpell, are falſly</hi> charged; with a briefe declaration of ſome ſuch monſtrous abuſes, as our Byſhops haue not bene aſhamed to foſter.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Waldegrave, featuring a swan standing on a wreath, within a border of intertwined snakes: a man's head below (McKerrow 227)</figDesc>
               <head>GOD IS MY HELPER</head>
               <p>GOD IS MY DEFENDER.</p>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON; <hi>Printed by</hi> Robert Walde-graue, 1584.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10166:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10166:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle reader, thou art not ignoraunt, that in this our Churche of Englande, there hath been a ſciſme for ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry yeares, which of late is growen ſo ſtrong, that vnleſſe the Lord looke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs in great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, it will in ſhort time bring foorth a very lamentable deſolation. Now, it is the part and duetie of euery true-harted Chriſtian, to do his beſt both by heartye prayer and otherwiſe ſo far as his calling doth reach, to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, ayde, and ſupport that ſide, which hath the truth. For this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration haue I beſtowed my poore trauell in writing this little dialogue. In which I haue as faithfully as I can, ſet downe the greateſt accuſations, and moſt vſuall crimes, that haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:10166:3"/> colour, which are ſlaunderouſlye caſt foorth, and laid to the charge of Gods faithfull meſſengers: with a ſhort aunſwere to ſhew the vanitie of the ſame. On the other ſide, I haue lightly touched as it were, the heades or fountaines of diuers corruptions, maintayned by the contrarye part, which are ſo groſſe &amp; manifeſt, that he which ſhall ſaye he knoweth not of them, maye well be ſuſpected for vntruth: and he that ſhall defende them, muſt put on his foreheade of braſſe. My ſute vnto thee, gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is no more but this, that thou wilt well waigh, and iudge vprightly, which part follow the ſteppes of the bleſſed Apoſtles, and ſo be the true miniſters of Ieſus chriſt. I know right well, ſome will bee offended at this kind of dealing, and ſay it is hurtful. But vnleſſe I would be vnfaithfull to my Lord and maſter Ieſus Chriſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutiful to his poore Church, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall to my ſoueraigne prince, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer I am bound to do more, I can with ſafe conſcience do no leſſe, then
<pb facs="tcp:10166:3"/> I haue here done. Some will ſay theſe are but words, and who can not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye make the like pretence for anye matter whatſoeuer. I will therefore note ſome particular cauſes, to ſhew the truth of my wordes. He that will be the faithfull ſeruaunt of Ieſus Chriſt, muſt ſtande for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Goſpell, and not holde his tongue when the courſe thereof is ſtayed and hindered. But the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers are ſo plentifull, will ſome man ſaye, that although here and there a few which will not conforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, be put to ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, yet the courſe of the goſpel is not hindered. I wold to God a true ſuruaye were made, that firſt all thoſe which haue faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully laboured, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they terme Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, being ſet aſide, they would take the veiw and number of ſuch as haue great titles and roomes, and yet feed not any flockes of ſheepe or lambes: and in the next place ſet thoſe which apply all their great learning, to get liuinges and dignities, not caring for ſoules: as namely to heape be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice
<pb facs="tcp:10166:4"/> vpon benefice, to ſeeke to bee Archdeacons, Deanes, and byſhops: For theſe ſeek after the things which are their owne, and not the thinges which are Chriſts: theſe ſerue not the Lord Ieſus, but their own belly: and though they can ſpeak like angels, yet the Church ſhall not bee bleſſed by them. For they are not ſent of God, they bee not the miniſters of Ieſus Chriſt, by whome he will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance his Goſpell. If yee can alſo number thoſe which goe vnder the names of Preachers, and doe either ſo ſeldome, ſo ſlenderly, and vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully teach, that their people are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the better. And in the laſt rancke place the vnable men, with thoſe of ſpotted life: I warrant yee the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant wil be <hi>Methemispar,</hi> as the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaketh. There ſhall need no A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetrician to take the account. Now to the ſecond point.</p>
            <p>When God hath prepared the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Manna, and appointed to his Church that ſhe ſhoulde eate her fill thereof, euen to the fatting of her
<pb facs="tcp:10166:4"/> ſoule, to make her liuely and ſtrong: and that her Children &amp; babes may ſucke from her breaſts the ſincere milk of the word: Who is there that hath a minde touched with any care of duety and ſeruice towardes her, that can holde his peace, and not complaine in her behalfe, when ſhee is denyed her right, in being debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of this heauenly bread, or at the leaſt ſo ſtinted and ſcanted, that ſhee can ſcarce haue ſufficient to preſerue life. Solomon ſaith, that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man conſidereth the ſoule of his beaſt, wheras the bowels of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are cruelty. A righteous man can not behold an Oxe, or an Horſe pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to death for want of foode, but that the mournefull voyce of the Dumbe Beaſte will ſtrike his heart, and mooue compasſion: and ſhall not the heart of a righteous man bleede? ſhall not his raines pricke? ſhall it not kindle and burſt out as a fire in him, ſhall hee not lament with pittie, when he beholdeth the Ladye and miſtreſſe of the worlde, the Lambes wife, euen the very deare
<pb facs="tcp:10166:5"/> ſpouſe to him that is Lord of Lords, depriued of her daylye foode? Can anye true Chriſtian man, with drye eyes looke vppon the leanneſſe and paleneſſe of her face, the feebleneſſe of her ioyntes, and weakeneſſe of her bodye? Her beautie ſhoulde bee ſo excellent, and her maieſtie ſo great, that ſhe ſhould be a terrour to thoſe enemyes which nowe deſpiſe and mocke her. Let them keepe ſilence that can, all good men will ſpeake and ſpeake againe in her behalfe: yea, euen againſt thoſe biſhops which doe her this great wronge, and ſeeke to deſtroy her children with famine. The bleſſed Apoſtle S. <hi>Paule,</hi> whoſe care was as tender ouer the weake ones of the Church, as the care of any mother towardes the babe that ſucketh vppon her breſtes,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.</note> ſaith <hi>Who is offended and I burne not?</hi> If there be anye ſparckle of his ſpirite in a man, how can he but burne, behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at this day, ſo many weak ones to ſtumble? both men and women, yong and old, in many places, which
<pb facs="tcp:10166:5"/> had receiued ſome taſte of the word, and began as greene plantes to bud being continually watred by Apollo: Nowe following the drought as it were of an whote Summer, the ſiluer dews being reſtrained fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dropping vpon them, and the fountains of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing waters ſhut vp, do wither away: yea, many are made to ſtagger, and doubt whether it were a true goſpell that was preached vnto them. For ſay they, if it were good, how ſhould any learned man go about to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it, or to put thoſe to ſilence that publiſh it? For the third point, is ther any man ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, how manifold trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons are practized by the papiſts, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like greedy bloud-houndes of hell, which thirſt for the very heart bloud of our ſouereign Queen? what conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtill in hope to bring their purpoſe to paſſe after ſo many repul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes? Is it the goodnes of their cauſe: no, it is the ignorance and blindnes of the vntaught multitude, in which their might is repoſed. Theſe night birds, know right well, that where
<pb facs="tcp:10166:6"/> the Sunne ſhineth, ther is ſmall place for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Let the people be taught to know wholſome doctrine, and they will neuer abide the rotten drugges of theſe Romiſh Apothecaries. Let them ſee the light, and be taught out of the bleſſed worde, that it is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to thoſe that rebell againſte their Prince, yea, though it be but a diſloyall minde, &amp; no outward thing practized. Let them feele what bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is come vnto them, by a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Mother in Iſrael, a nurſe of Gods Churche, and that they are deepely bound, not onely vppon their knees to powre out plentifull prayers vnto God for her: but alſo, that it is their duety to aduenture their liues for her defence: and you ſhall haue them farre from giuing eare vnto traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous perſuaſions of Ieſuites, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary Prieſtes. Beholde, for this cauſe, how thoſe that are known fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourers of the Romiſh Religion, do now beſtirre them, to throwe downe the Preachers, by procuring matters of complaint againſt them vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:10166:6"/> byſhoppes. If this diſhonour be not done vnto Chriſt, which I haue men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, this iniurye to his poore Churche, and daunger to our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Queene, by heartning and ſtrengthning the handes of her eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: let this my doing bee coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſedicious, as I am out of doubt, ſome will not ſticke very malitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to terme it. But if it bee as I haue ſayde, and as many thouſandes with griefe doe beholde, and can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (by whome let me be tried, and accounted ſhameleſſe if I lye) then I craue, that I may not bee blamed for ſpeaking in ſo waighty cauſes, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a little of thoſe things which all the Seruauntes of God ought to cry out of: But to what purpoſe, or wher ſhall there be redreſſe fought for? O ye Byſhops, euen in this, repent, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, repent in time that GOD may haue mercye vppon yee. Will yee bee offended with him that ſhall giue ye wholeſome counſell? or will yee ſay that yee are wrongfully char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged? good counſel ye wil ſay is neuer
<pb facs="tcp:10166:7"/> to be reiected, then may it eaſily be prooued, that ye ſtand in neede of it. To let other thinges paſſe, ought not the miniſters of the Goſpell to bee paterns and examples vnto the flock both in wholſom doctrine and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuerſation? ought they not to be the lights of the worlde, and the ſalt of the earth, to ſeaſon the hearts of the people with ſpirituall graces, &amp; to ſhine vnto them as ſtarres, that they may ſee the paths of life? ought they not to feed the lords flock with the bread of life, to lead the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the green paſtures, and vnto the ſtreams of liuing waters? ought they not to ſeeke vp that which goeth aſtray, to heale that which is diſeaſed, and to carry the tender Lambes in their boſom? are your miniſters with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye haue filled the church ſuch? or will yee ſeeke for excuſes to make your fault light? ſurely if ye do not repent, ye cannot bee ſaued. God doth not reſpect the perſonnes of men. Wil ye repent at the laſt, and leaue the thing vnrefourmed when ye dye? what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce
<pb facs="tcp:10166:7"/> will that be? will ye make your prayers vnto God, and will he heare them? your garmentes being ful of bloud, euen the bloud of many ſoules that periſh for want of foode: yee would haue thoſe that be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt and wallowe in their ſinnes to be counted Chriſtians, that it might not be knowne, that the want of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching deſtroyeth ſouls. But the word of the Lorde will bee too ſtronge for ye, which teacheth manifeſtly the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesſity thereof. Are yee aſhamed to bee reprooued by your inferiours, when your ſinne is manifeſt? It is a ſhame to continue, but no ſhame at all for a man to amend his fault. Do ye count it a diſcredite to yeelde any thing at all vnto thoſe which are your inferiours, &amp; haue alſo their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities? count it no diſcredit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent &amp; yeelde vnto the word of God, which is free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all impurity. Looke not vppon the offences of any that reprooue yee, neither bee delighted to heare ſlanderous things of them: For their ſinnes ſhall be no helpe at
<pb facs="tcp:10166:8"/> all to couer yours before God, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ye may make them ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of your doinges before men. The Lorde God of his mercy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen your eyes, and take pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his deſolate peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:10166:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Dialogue</hi> concerning the ſtrife of our Church.</head>
            <list>
               <head>The Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers:</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Orthodoxos, <hi>a Diuine.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Philodoxos, <hi>a Lawyer.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Philochrematos, <hi>a By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Chaplaine.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Philedonos, <hi>an Inne-holder.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philedonos.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, ye bee all heartilie welcome; I pray you be as merrie as though your cheere were greater. If we had better, ye ſhoulde haue better: but I hope ye will bee content with ſuch as God ſendeth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>Our cheere doth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:10166:9"/> content vs very well mine hoſte, we do thanke ye for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philedonos.</speaker>
               <p>I could teem it were better: but ſurely In-keeping is cold in ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry places ouer it hath bin, &amp; that cauſeth vs to make ſlender prouiſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philoch.</speaker>
               <p>How ſhold y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be, ther be as many trauellers as euer there were.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philedonos.</speaker>
               <p>Oh ſir, I graunt ye: but our chiefe gaine hereabout doth not ſtande in that, I haue knowne when a dozen or ſixteene Gentlemen and wealthie yeomen haue met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and made merrie foure or fiue daies, or a weeke, at cards or Bowls, as the time did ſerue. Nowe all good fellowſhip is laide aſide, the worlde is waxen ſtark nought.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>In deede that was a good helpe to Inne-holders, and I think it be much left in manie places, men waxe more couetous &amp; worldlie, they haue not the care they had to maintain loue &amp; friendſhip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philedonos.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot tell whether they bee more couetous: but there be ſo manie new-fangled Preachers, it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:10166:9"/> is greate pittie that they be ſuffered: they marre all, for they deſtroie all good houſe-keeping.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philocrematos.</speaker>
               <p>It is verie true: I haue knowne as much meat ſpent in one houſe at a Chriſtmas, as is nowe ſpente in three, a lamentable thing, the poore do rue it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philedonos.</speaker>
               <p>They keep ſmall hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalitie themſelues, and not content with that, they preach and crie out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it in other men, I am vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but yet I think a preacher ſhold keepe good hoſpitality, and commend it in others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philocrematos.</speaker>
               <p>Naie ye ſay true, for the apoſtle willeth them to be har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berouſe. <hi>1. Tim. 3.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Ye doe not well, to ſoothe and vpholde mine hoſte in his euill ſpeeches, for he doth ſhewe him ſelfe to be a verie groſſe and carnall man: he is al for the luſts &amp; pleaſures of the fleſh, voide of the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, not hauing anie taſte of ſpiritual things, one of thoſe which (as the Scripture ſaith) make their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10166:10"/> bellie their God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Yee miſtake mine hoſte, ye do him great wrong, to giue ſuch ſeuere and ſharpe ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him: I obſerued and weied all his ſpeeches, ſo farre as I can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, he vttered nothing worthie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke: hee complaineth, and I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant yée, not without cauſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Inhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders haue ſmal reſort, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good houſkée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping is decayed, &amp; men be new-fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled and ouer preciſe, do ye not think they are to be blamed, as thoſe which do more hurt then good? I ſuppoſe ye are not of that minde, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Innekéeping to be a lawful and honeſt vocation, then ye muſt alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, to ſeek ſuch gaine as that they may liue. They paie great houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, bedding &amp; other furniture is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie coſtly. In a worde, they buy all things deare. How ſhall they be able to keepe open there doores, if it be not lawful for men to meet togeather, to ſpende their time in honeſt recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? It doth nouriſh friendſhip. I am bolde to ſpeake in defence of mine
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:10166:10"/> Hoſt: If he had any worſe meaning, I am deceiued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodox.</speaker>
               <p>I do not thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his meaning was worſe then yours: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth that colour of words which you goe about to colour it with all, hide the nakedneſſe thereof: ſo farre off is it, from proouing his meaning or yours to bee good, hauing ſcarce a ſhew of reaſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>If there bee ſcarce a ſhew of reaſon in my ſpéech, you may the more eaſely confute it. But it wil be harder for you to excuſe your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable &amp; ſeuere damning of men, then for me to mainteine my ſaying.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodox.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe I ſaid mine Hoſt is a carnal man, without the knowledge of God, one that is all for the luſtes and pleaſures of the fleſhe, one of thoſe which make their belly their God: Yee ſay I do vncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably damn men, Ye did not heare mee pronounce a finall ſentence vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him: But if he continue in the caſe he is now in, there is no doubt. Let his owne wordes giue euidence.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:10166:11"/> He ſaid the worlde is waxed ſtarke nought, becauſe men do not meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, to drinck and playe as they were wont. The Prophet ſaith, <hi>Wo be vnto thoſe which call good euill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſay 5.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and euill good.</hi> The Lorde condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth drunkenneſſe, and gluttonie, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſſe, miſpending the time, vaine ſpeeches, railing, fretting, quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſwearing, coueting other mens goods, vndoing and beggering Wife and Children, by ſpending their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: all theſe thinges are rife, and ouerflow among thoſe which do méet togeather at play: When the Lorde ſaith theſe things be euill, and mine Hoſt ſaith the worlde is naught for learning them: Is it not plaine that he is a carnal man, and knoweth not God. You colour it, and ſaye Inhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſit at a great rent, and paie dear for all thinges, and they muſt liue. If you did know or conſider, how cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed a thing it is to gather gooddes by ſuch meanes, you woulde confeſſe it were a thouſande folde better for to begge. He ſaith the Preachers which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:10166:11"/> cry out againſt ſuch things be new-fangled, is he not thereby apparant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie knowne to be a belly God. You would faine helpe him, and yee ſaye, if men be new fangled and ouer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe: are they not to be blamed? Yes no doubt. But you muſt ſhew that it is to bee new-fangled and ouer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, for to publiſhe the holy worde of God, againſt ſuch filthie vices. Yee ſay all of yee, that good houſe keping doth decay, and the poore they rue it. The houſe kéeping which you mean, is that confuſed ryot, where there is aboundaunce of meate and drinke, ſpent euen as well as if it were caſt vnto the Dogs. Some rich man doth keepe open houſe for twelue dayes, there gather all the idle vnthriftes, euen the ſcum &amp; dregs of the people: There is ſuch reuill night and day, that if a man that hath a godly mind come in, hee doth thinke he commeth into a little hell. The good creatures of God are waſted vpon moſt filthie perſonnes. Some man doth looſe ſo much at Cardes, that his wife and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:10166:12"/> his children do fare hardly a moneth after. The poore may rue that there is more caſt away in one daye, then woulde ſerue them a whole weeke. The Preachers they keepe not Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalitie (ſaith mine Hoſt) becauſe they do not follow this order: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſundry haue not the wealth to do it. And thus mine Hoſt and thoſe which be iumpe of his religion, doe cry out ſtil to haue the paunch filled. If they maye haue one which will make them good cheere, though hee neuer miniſter vnto them any ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall food, yet they are aboundantly ſatiſfied &amp; contented. But if he bring the foode of the ſoule neuer ſo plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vnto them, and not able to doe the other, they make no reckoning thereof: Which doth moſt plainely ſhewe, that they are ſuch as Chriſte ſpake vnto, <hi>Iohn. 6.</hi> which ſought him becauſe he had fedde their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. And as for the friendſhip which is gotten and nouriſhed by meeting at play: It is ſmall friendſhip when they fall to it by the eares. If they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:10166:12"/> doe agree, yet the loue and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which is tyed togeather with ſuch cordes, is but in the fleſhe, and not that holye and ſpirituall loue which God requireth of Chriſtians.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>I did demaunde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, if they bee not to bee blamed, which are new fangled, and ouer preciſe, as thoſe which doe more hurt then good? I woulde it were not ſo eaſie to prooue as it is, that they doe more hurt then good, by beeing not onely ouer precize, and new fangled: but raſhe and vndiſcreet yea (if yee will) vngodly. And why? Becauſe they preach againſt ſuch filthie vices and publiſhe the holy worde of God? No Sir, that is good. Yee maye not put me to prooue them therefore to be in fault. No man wil ſaye they do hurt thereby. But this is vndiſcreet, and worthy blame, that while they make ſharpe inuectiues againſt the abuſes, they vtterly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues which are indifferent and lawfull. Becauſe ſome when they play, doe fret and ſweare, they will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:10166:13"/> alowe no man to doe it: Some doe for couetouſneſſe, reprooue thoſe: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe it to paſſe away the time in honeſt recreation, not for anye hurt, Why ſhoulde they be blamed, now while they thus condemne the thinges them ſelues, and ſtay not in reproouing the abuſes: it cauſeth que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions and contentions, and breach of charitie among the people. This is a ſore wound in a common wealth, Where the ſubiects are to be kept in vnitie one with an other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>The Iewes tooke vp ſtones to ſtone our ſauiour Chriſt, and when hee aunſwered and ſaide, <hi>Many good workes haue I ſhewed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>for which of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe ye ſtone me?</hi> They had their excuſe ready, <hi>For thy good workes we ſtone thee not, but for thy blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, that thou being a man, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thy ſelfe God.</hi> Such is the excuſe and pretence which you and others make againſt the Preachers of the Goſpell, let them preach the worde in Gods name, that is good: Let them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:10166:13"/> alſo beate downe vice, wee can not blame them therfore: But we blame them that they deale raſhlye, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning thinges lawfull. Well, let it be graunted, that to play at cardes and dice, is a thing of it ſelfe indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and lawfull: Yet it muſt (before the vſe therof can be free) be deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded whether it be expedient, If there come much hurt by it many wayes? Is it meete that men for their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſhould vſe it? Will it beare vs out for a carnall recreation, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye the glorye of God, and the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and ſoules of men? Shall men for that little good, which they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine to reape thereby, ſow and plant a multitude of ſhamefull vices? But you put a difference, though ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe playe, yet other vſe it rightly: Who are they which vſe it rightly? Are they not the Godly and the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt? Shall not then their example harten and harden the other in their wicked abuſes? Is not this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon defence, ſuch a man is a wiſe man, &amp; a learned man, he plaieth, woulde he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:10166:14"/> play if it were not good? thus for their pleaſure they throw down the honor of god, while they giue ſtrength vnto others. Wee ought to forgoe a farre greater matter then pleaſure, rather then vice ſhould be encouraged, and mens ſoules deſtroied by your occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. It is a fooliſh cauill which men vſe againſt this: Many ſay they are drunkerdes &amp; gluttons: many abuſe their apparell: therefore we may not eate nor drinke, nor put on clothes, if it be ſo, leaſt wee doe bolden them in their ſinne. That is nothing like, for theſe thinges are ſuch as can not bee ſpared: thoſe other may be forborne yet no man the worſe, there would be no queſtions nor contentions, nor breach of charitie among the people for this matter, if the multitude were not more zealous in the defence of their carnall luſtes and pleaſures, then they be for the honour of God: but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yée ſay the preachers, which beate down ſuch things are vngodly, ye do therein very groſely ouerſhoote your ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:10166:14"/>
               <speaker>Philedonos.</speaker>
               <p>I maruell why they ſhould make themſelues more holie then others? I know ſundrie graue Diuines, other manner of men then any of them be, which will take their recreation, when time ſerueth amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g their honeſt neighbors. I wiſſe they are more preciſe then wiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Indéed mine hoſte, there be too many of thoſe graue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, which beſtowe mo howres vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ale-bench, at Mumchance or at Mawe, then they do in catechiſing their people. In deede ſuch as theſe, are they, by whome you are moſt edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: they are other maner of men for your turne, then ſuch as both by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and conuerſation ouerthrowe vngodlie riot: but I will leaue you in your wiſe iudgement, and heare what this Gentleman will anſwere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>I did not groſelie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſhoote my ſelfe, in terming them vngodly, if there were any groſenes, it was in your vnderſtanding, and not in my wordes: for it was not my meaning that they are wicked, onely
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10166:15"/> becauſe they condemne ſuch thinges: they haue other faultes beſides that, dothe not the Scripture pronounce them wicked, which diſobeye their Prince, doe not theſe vtterlie refuſe to obey the princes Lawes? ſhall we terme them good, when the worde of God prooueth them to be euill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>The phariſees rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thus againſt Chriſte Ieſus, <hi>this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not of God, becauſe he keepeth not the ſabboth:</hi> this is a moſte ſure principle, that he which breaketh the Sabboth is not of God: they thought themſelues cockſure, that he obſerued not the ſabboth, becauſe he healed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, but therein they erred. The pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes vſe this, which is an vnfalllble trueth againſte thoſe which profeſſe the Goſpel: they be all heretikes and Siſmatiques which ſeperate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from the Church of Chriſt: but when they ſhoulde prooue that thoſe which forſake the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> forſake the true Church, therein they are grauelled: the ſame kinde of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, doe you and ſuch as you are,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:10166:15"/> vſe againſt the miniſters of Chriſte: they bee wicked ſay you, which diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey Princes: who denieth that? the authoritie and power of Princes is of God. <hi>He that reſiſteth the power,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>reſiſteth God: and ſo doth procure to himſelfe damnation:</hi> But nowe ſhew your cunning in this point, to prooue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe are diſobedient vnto Princes, againſt whom you ſpeake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>There needeth no greate cunning for that matter, for the thing it ſelfe is manifeſt, doe not the Lawes of this realme command diuerſe thinges, and are there not ſundrie which refuſe to do them? ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be diſobedient vnto princes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot tell howe great knowledge, ye haue in the law: but your ſkill in Logicke is ſmall, and leſſe in diuinitie, if ye mainteine and holde this for a neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence or concluſion, they be diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient vnto Princes, becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to doe ſome thinges which are commaunded by the lawe. For put caſe a moſte Godlye and Chriſtian
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:10166:16"/> Prince, with graue and wiſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers doe ſet foorth and eſtabliſhe ſome thinges which agree not with Gods word, and yet they ſuppoſe that the ſame thinges are agreeable vnto the word. For what Princes or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers are ſo wiſe, but that they may faile in ſome pointes? Shall a man then which doth ſée a thing comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the lawe, to bee againſte the word, and therefore doth refuſe to doe it, be counted diſobedient to Princes? Do not you know that which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle teacheth. <hi>Actes. 4.</hi> We muſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God rather then men? Doe not you knowe alſo, that although the thing be lawfull which is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and a man through want of ſkil, or weakenes of conſcience, doth feare &amp; doubt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame thing is euil, and yet doth it, that he condemneth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his deed, according to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which <hi>S, Paule</hi> teacheth. <hi>Rom. 14. ver. 23.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>You charge me with vnſkilfulnes, becauſe of that conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which I made. But I doubt yee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:10166:16"/> will not very eaſily diſprooue the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the conſequence: for if theſe be not <hi>coniugata,</hi> Diſobedience and to diſobey, I know not what are. You colour the matter with this, that we muſt obey onely in things which are not repugnaunt vnto Gods worde: who ſhall be iudge in theſe caſes, or to which part ſhal men giue credite? All the wiſeſt in the land, and cheefe in learning doe aſſemble in parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and with all the care and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe they can, make and eſtabliſh lawes. Now when they haue done, a few other, and farre inferiour vnto them, ſhal miſlike, &amp; vndo that which they haue done: Theſe ſhall take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to controwle the Nobility, the Iudges and Biſhops of the land, and to be wiſer then all they: would ſo many Godly learned Fathers ſet out anie thing that is not ſounde? It is very abſurd, if men had any wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or diſcretion in them, for to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne. If we ſhall not truſt thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhall we truſt them? why ſhould not they be ſatiſfied? why ſhould they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:10166:17"/> be more preciſe or ſcrupulous, then their betters? It is a wilfulneſſe in them. It is pitty there is no ſharper puniſhment to compell them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſſe that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, and to diſobey be <hi>Coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gata:</hi> but yet it is eaſie ynough to diſprooue the neceſſity of your argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For there is no diſobedience, but where a man refuſeth to obey, in thinges that are good: Where God enioineth no obedience, there can bee no diſobedience by refuſing. As for example, ſome prince doth command his ſubiectes to worſhip Idols, or ſome other thing which God doth forbid them: they refuſe to do it, not of ſtubberneſſe but of conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God: will ye ſay they be diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient? but you ſée well inough that this weapon wil not ſerue, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yee are content to caſt it down, and to retier your ſelfe into a ſtrong hold, as you imagine. For who ſhall iudge of maters whether they be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to gods word (ſay you) which part ſhal we beleeue? What are yee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:10166:17"/> a Papiſt? Yee runne into the ſame holde that they doe when they fight. They demand in like ſort who ſhall iudge, &amp; which part is worthier of credite? If wee ſhall confeſſe your argument to be good and ſound, how ſhall we denie it when it commeth from them bumbaſted and ſet foorth with greater might? For when you ſaye, all the wiſeſt and learnedeſt, of Nobility, Iudges, and biſhops haue done it, howe ſhall a fewe inferiour perſonnes controll them or be wiſer then they? Wil they alowe that which is not agreeable vnto Gods word? Then the Papiſtes may ſay, when as their religion hath been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by all the wiſeſt Princes, Biſhops, and Counſellers, with ſo general conſent of ſo many ages, not of one Realme, but aſſembled out of a great ſort of Countries and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces: How ſhall a fewe (for the Nobles, Iudges, Biſhoppes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in a Parliament holden in one kingdome are but a fewe vnto theire multitude) controll them?
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:10166:18"/> If twentie or thirty learned byſhops in one Land aſſembled together, can not ſet foorth or allow any thing but that which is good, how ſhall fowre or fiue hundred choiſe Fathers out of all countries be ouerſeene? Oh ſir, if this were a good reaſon, the Goſpell might lye in the duſt: If it bee good with vs, why ſhoulde it not be good when the Papiſts doe vſe it? Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallye when they haue more right vnto it, becauſe theire multitude hath beene farre greater. Howe wiſe you and manye other which vſe this argument, doe take your ſelues to be. I pray yee did ye not vſe it in the daies of Quéene <hi>Marie?</hi> will you refuſe to go vnto the maſſe? will you be wiſer then the Queene &amp; the Counſell, &amp; all the learned Byſhops? Doubtles in this point yee are very wiſe, that ye haue layd a foundation that will beare any frame. Yée may go through all times, and chaunges of religion. For whatſoeuer a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament doth ſet vp, yee will haue it by and by no further examined.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:10166:18"/>
               <speaker>Philodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>The general counſels of the Papiſts are not like the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: neither do ye well to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them ſo togeather. For they looked to mans inuentions, but our Byſhops haue regarded only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Let that be ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, as in deede God bee bleſſed there is great difference, albeit the Popiſhe Byſhops profeſſed to do all by the word. Yet neuertheleſſe you muſt proue that thirty or fortie lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Byſhops looking only to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God, can not ſwerue in any thing from truth, before this can follow, that no part of their doings may be controwled.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Ye do not heere mee ſaye that no part of their doing may be controwled: but I ſay this, when ſo many graue lerned byſhops haue decreed it, ſhal it be controwled by a few greene and light heades? Can thoſe which are nothing ſo many nor ſo learned, nor in no reſpect to be eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teemed ſo much, ſee more then they?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:10166:19"/> It is like as if all the iudges in the Lande had agreed vppon a caſe, and an vtter bareſter or one which hath ſtudied the Lawes, but two or three yeares; ſhoulde controule them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Yee liken it as if all the Iudges in the Lande had agreed vpon a Caſe, and then a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye young Studente in the Lawe, ſhould take vpon him to controwle them all: when a fewe (as you ſay) greene heades, refuſe to doe euerye thing that the Byſhoppes conclude vppon. I knowe it is a ſtraunge thing and incredible, that all the Iudges in the land ſhould miſſe in a Caſe, and not bee able to ſée that which ſome one of ſmall knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſhould ſee: but yet yee muſt knowe, that the Caſe is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather lyke in Heauenlye mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which men can not reache vnto by ſtudy &amp; wit, as they do vnto earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but wher God doth inwardly ligh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten &amp; teach by his ſpirit. Now God hath not tyed him ſelfe vnto multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:10166:19"/> nor vnto yeares, but where it pleaſeth him to reueale: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one poore man bringing reaſon and authoritie out of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, is more to be eſteemed, then tenne thouſande great Biſhoppes, ſtanding vppon their conſent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out warraunt of the worde. The Prieſtes in the lawe boldened them ſelues with the like reaſon, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult to ſtrike <hi>Ieremias:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>The law</hi> (ſay they) <hi>ſhall not periſh from the Prieſt, and counſell from the wiſe, and the worde from the Prophet.</hi> In like maner worldly wiſe men doe ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie blind them ſelues, hanging their faith vpon probabilitie, and not ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching déeply into the matter. Againe yée doe falſlye and vntruely in your compariſon, to liken the one part as it were to al the iudges in the land, &amp; the other to a yong ſtude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the law. For, ſet the Papiſts a ſide, &amp; the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of learned men againſt whom you ſpeake, are more in number the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the biſhops, Deanes, Archdeacons and biſhops Chaplains in this land.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:10166:20"/> For ye muſt looke vpon the faithfull ſeruaunts of God in other Lands. If yee reſpect learning, there are none in our Land (but ſuch as are impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent) that wil compare with ſome of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſhould not we thinke there bee as manye learned men of our lande, as in any other?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>God be bleſſed there be great lerned men in our land, but yet I doubt not but they wil confes, that the Lord raiſed vp ſome in other Landes, whome he made the cheefe and principal Inſtrumentes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore his Goſpell, the fruite of whoſe labours, doth ſpread ſo farre, that in all Churches, they are famous: yea there is no one man which is a true miniſter of Ieſus Chriſt, but he hath iuſt cauſe to bleſſe and praiſe God for them: Such was M. <hi>Luther,</hi> M. <hi>Caluine,</hi> M. <hi>Beza,</hi> M. <hi>Tremellius</hi> and others. I know in deede ther bee of our men, whom the Church might ſpare wel ynough for any good they euer did vnto it, which will not ſtick
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:10166:20"/> to compare with the beſt of theſe, &amp; to take themſelues rather to be their ſuperiours. Other men wil ſo eſtéem of them alſo, when they haue approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them ſelues to bee ſuch faithfull ſeruauntes of Chriſt, and haue done the like good to the Churche, that thoſe other did: in the meane time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery wiſe man will iudge as he fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>I know theſe whom you name are famous men, but what haue they to doe with our church?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Haue you got that by the end alſo? ſurely I cannot tell what other men may iudge: but in my iudgement, it is a very prophane and a very wicked ſaying. Is there any God but one? any faith but one? any Church but one? Is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole Churche in all places in the worlde Gods familie? Hath he not giuen one booke of the holy &amp; ſacred ſcriptures to teache and gouerne the ſame, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery part therof? Were not thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> principall Inſtruments of the Lord, to expounde and open the myſteries
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:10166:21"/> of God vnto his church? did they not teach &amp; declare the counſels of God onely out of his word? Is our church then the Church of Chriſte, and hath their doctrine nothing to do with it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>I know right well, that their doctrine which they teach out of Gods word, which is the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of faith, doth belong indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently to the whole Church. Becauſe as you ſay, there is but one Church, and one faith. But in ſome externall matters one Church may differ from an other. And in that reſpect, euery Church is not tied to the outwarde forme of the Church at <hi>Geneua,</hi> in euery particular. There be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunces of perſons, times and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which maye make ſome vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>One Church maye differ from an other in ſome exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall matter: let that be graunted, as I know not who doth deny it. Is that a ſufficient cauſe for men to ſaye, what hath maiſter <hi>Caluine</hi> or maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> or others to doe with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:10166:21"/> our Church? Haue not the excellent ſeruaunts of God, taught that point alſo by the Scriptures, which you ſpeak off, that churches may vary in ſome externall matters? How then can it be ſaide that our Church hath nothing to doe with their doctrine? I doe not ſpeake as though we were to depende vppon men, further then they prooue their doctrine by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures. But when God hath raiſed vp ſpeciall inſtrumentes, and made them lightes to his people, it muſte needes proceede from a vile minde to ſaye, what haue they to doe with our Church? Such mens fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are to be looked vnto, as thoſe which are not to bee put in truſte with the Spouſe of Chriſt. For this is out of all doubt, that as thoſe other are manifeſted vnto the worlde to be rare and ſpeciall ſeruauntes of God, for the ſeruice of his ſonne, and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his people: ſo theſe by deman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding ſo diſdainfully what they haue to do with our Church, giue manifeſt cauſe of ſuſpicion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be none of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:10166:22"/> Gods houſhold. For either they muſt prooue that thoſe excellent men, did not deale faithfully in Gods mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (which they ſhall neuer be able to doe) or elſe confeſſe themſelues to be vntruſty. Who is ſo fooliſh, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he can ſée whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty power of Gods ſpirit haue ſpread the light of the Goſpell, and thrown downe the Kingdome of Antichriſt, are reiected or little ſet by, that there is no faithful mind, eſpecially when it is by thoſe which them ſelues doe hurt and no good, to the furtheraunce of mens ſaluation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>Gentleman, by your patience, maye it pleaſe you to let me aunſwere, not that I thinke you vnable to confute ſuch friuolous ſpeech, but becauſe I am pricked, and can holde no longer. I woulde faine knowe who they are whome you meane, which do hurt, &amp; no good, in our Church. If you meane the cheefe of the cleargy, God be thanked your ſlanderous tongue is not able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credite them: they are well knowne
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:10166:22"/> to be graue, wiſe, learned, and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and therefore of all others do the moſt good, and the leaſt hurt in the Church. If yee meane the Puritans or Preciſians, all wiſe men wil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée with you: for in déede it can not be ſhewed that they do any good, but I am able to prooue, that they doe much hurt: for they be Sciſmatikes, and make diuiſion in the Church, a thing much to be abhorred of al god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mindes: they are the cauſe that there be ſo many Papiſtes, for what maketh them to be offended, and to refuſe to come to the Churche, but this that we do not agrée among our ſelues, but theſe are not thoſe whom you meane.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>I ſée you take it in great ſnuffe, that I ſaide, there are which doe hurte and no good in the Church. You woulde knowe whome I meane: But it muſt needes bee meant (as you take it) eyther of the cheefe of the Cleargie, or elſe of thoſe whome you tearme Puritans and Preciſians. For the firſt yee ſay
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:10166:23"/> they bee well knowne to bee graue, wiſe, learned and Godly. I ſuppoſe by the chiefe of the Cleargie, you meane Biſhops, Deanes, and Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, and Biſhops Chaplaynes, And ſo you come in the number your ſelfe, beeing a Biſhops Chaplaine. I doe ſuppoſe that the greateſt part of theſe are graue and learned, and it were a verye lamentable thing that none of them ſhould be Godly. I doe verilye ſuppoſe, that among theſe there be ſome which are not ſo drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with couetouſneſſe and ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but that they haue their ſpeciall care for the aduauncement of Gods Goſpell, and the ſaluation of mens ſoules: But will yee therefore cléere and iuſtifie all? But as for the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanes and Preciſians, yee ſay they do no good, and you can prooue they doe much hurt. You doe alſo ſhew, wherein they be Sciſmatikes, and make diuiſion in the Church. They giue offence to the Papiſtes. No doubte theſe bee abominable vices, and thoſe that be giltie of them, the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:10166:23"/> woe and curſſe of God doth hange o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their heades. But your bare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation maye not carrye away the matter, you muſte prooue thoſe men to bee ſuch, whome you call Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>It is a ſore mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which yee put me vnto. I praye yee what neede is there of anye fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proofe, when the thing is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to all the worlde? Who doth not ſee that there is a Sciſme in our Church, both among miniſters and people? Who doth not ſee who are the cauſe of it? When a Church is eſtabliſhed, and there doth ariſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention therein: are thoſe the Sciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes which defende the ſtate and would haue it quiet: or thoſe which rayſe vp vnquietneſſe? Do the chiefe Prelates make the Sciſme in our Church, or the Puritanes? It is well knowne that they labour to haue it in peace, but theſe other are the cauſe of vnquietneſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>You make verye
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:10166:24"/> light of the matter, as a thing ſo eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that there needeth no proofe. And to make the euidencie appeare, yée take this for your grounde, that where a Church is eſtabliſhed, thoſe which defend the ſtate thereof to hold it in quiet canne not bee Sciſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes. On the contrarye parte: thoſe which make any vnquietneſſe to the ſtate thereof, can not but be Sciſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes. If yee will haue no further conſideration but ſo, then ſurely mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Luther,</hi> maiſter <hi>Caluine,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, are iuſtly charged by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes to be Sciſmatikes. For there was a ſtate eſtabliſhed: the Pope &amp; his Prelates were deſirous to hold it in quiet. The other part yee knowe did diſquiet it. Yet neuertheleſſe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one which hath anie true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God will confeſſe, that the Pope and his Cardinals are the ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes, and that the other were Gods true ſeruantes. And why? He is the Sciſmatike which doth depart from the trueth and maintaine cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, although it be with neuer
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:10166:24"/> ſo great pretence of peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For ſhal there be peace againſt God? Shal there be peace againſt the truth? Shall there be peace to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of mens ſoules, and laying waſt of the church? On the other ſide, ſhall thoſe bee called Sciſmatikes, which ſtand for the truth, which ſéek the ſaluation of mens ſoules? Yée muſt bring better ſtuffe, vnleſſe yee will fight as the Papiſtes do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>This compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which you make, is verye vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual: for the ſtate of our Church is not like the ſtate of the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> We haue the Goſpell eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed and ſincerely taught, there is Idolatrie and all kinde of falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine ſet foorth and maintained. The Pope with his Cardinals and By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops be the Sciſmatikes, becauſe they maintaine that which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, and goe againſt the truth. And therfore they do lewdly and vniuſtly charge maiſter <hi>Luther,</hi> maiſter <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine,</hi> and the reſt to be Sciſmatikes, which in deed ſet foorth the truth. And
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:10166:25"/> therefore I ſay ſtill, they be Sciſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes which trouble and diſturbe the vnitie &amp; peace of that Church, where the Goſpell is purely taught. It is you that muſte bring better ſtuffe, ſuch as you are, do rather conſpire with the Papiſtes, to reaſon as they doe: and to fight with ſuch weapons as they doe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Yee doe me wrong, in ſaying that I compare the ſtate of our Church, with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> For they maintaine Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and falſe doctrine, as you haue truely ſaid, and we haue the Goſpell eſtabliſhed and ſincerely taught. A brought in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but as an example, to ſhew that they are not alway Sciſmatikes which go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtate of a Church: neither are they alwayes to bee excuſed as free from Sciſme, which maintaine vnitie and peace. For I pray yee tell me, if in a Church there be foule abuſes, and ſuch as are intollerable, as bringing hazarde both to the Church and common wealth, one
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:10166:25"/> part cry out againſt them, an other part defend and cheriſhe them, who are the Sciſmatikes? True it is, there woulde bee no ſtirre, if none did finde fault. But will yee ſaye they bee Sciſmatikes, which doe publiſhe the truth, to throw downe falſehood? Or will yee ſaye thoſe are no Sciſmatikes which do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande and fight againſt the trueth, becauſe they woulde haue an vnitie and quiet eſtate?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>I doe graunt that where there are intollerable corruptions, thoſe are Sciſmatikes which doe maintaine the ſame. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they make a rent from God and from his truth, howſoeuer they be at vnitie amongeſt them ſelues. I doe alſo confeſſe that it is the part of euerye Godly Preacher, in due time and place, and in good ſorte to reprooue ſuch corruptions, and although there ſhoulde be a Sciſme by that meanes, yet they are not to bee accounted Sciſmatikes, for they haue doone but their duetie.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:10166:26"/> But what is this to the purpoſe? Doth this diſcharge our Puritanes from Sciſme? Our Church hath no ſuch abuſes. They be but toyes and trifles which they ſtriue about. It is a great wickednes for men to make a broyle, and ſtriue in the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout matters of no importaunce. It were much better for them to imploy them ſelues to teach the people to know their dutie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodox.</speaker>
               <p>I am fully of your mind in this point, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is a great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make any broyle in the Church for trifles and matters of no importance, the peace of the Church ought to be deare vnto men. And I doe not thinke there is anye Church which is ſo pure in doctrine and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, but it hath ſome little ſpots. You doe alſo graunt as much as I doe require, when yee ſay thoſe are Sciſmatikes which maintaine intollerable corruptions: and ſuch as reprooue them doe but their due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For it muſt follow that ſome of our chiefe Prelates do bring in and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:10166:26"/> maintaine intollerable abuſes, that they bee the Sciſmatikes and the cauſe of all miſchiefe in our Church: and then the Preciſian as you terme him, doth but diſcharge his duety in finding fault.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>I tolde yee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and I tell yee againe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine I doe affirme it, that they bee trifles which our Puritans do ſtriue about. If you can ſhew anye intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable corruption which our lawe doth eſtabliſh, yee ſay ſomewhat For our chiefe Prelates mainetaine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the lawes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>You tell me they be trifles, when I know that your tongue can tell nothing but truth. I will beleeue yee. Yee woulde haue me ſhew any ſuch abuſe eſtabliſhed by our lawe, as is intollerable. I tell yee flatly my iudgement is this, that the verye grounde and ſubſtaunce of our lawes is the worde of God. And that the verye minde and intent of the lawe is, that whatſoeuer is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and his worde, ſhoulde
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:10166:27"/> be throwne downe. And I doe not take that man to iudge ſo dutifully, as he ought to doe of his Prince and noble Counſellers, which doth not thinke that their whole purpoſe was to ſet vp Gods truth, and to throw downe wickednes: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made ſuch lawes as did tend to that effect. And alſo I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the groſſe abuſes in our Church, are either by neglect of the lawes, or elſe by peruerting the true meaning of the lawes, by ſome of thoſe which ſhoulde put them in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution. Will not you affirme that our lawes haue this minde and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie in them, that nothing ſhoulde bee which is againſte the manifeſt worde of God, and which deſtroyeth his Church, for the maintenaunce whereof in deed, our lawes were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>What if I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that our lawes haue this minde and equitie in them, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhoulde be, which is againſte the manifeſt word of God, or which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:10166:27"/> deſtroyeth his Church, as in deede I doe affirme? What can yee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thereby, but onely this which maketh flatlye againſt yee: That looke howe much more Godlye the lawes are, ſo much greater is their offence in diſobeying them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>That which you ſaye is true, the more Godlye the lawes are, the more is the offence of thoſe which diſobeye them. But giue me leaue now, to ſhew where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in diſobedience lyeth, and to gather that which I perceiue you do not yet ſee. The law of God is abſolutely perfect, both in the purpoſe of requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that which is Godly, and alſo in expreſſing the ſame in moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect forme. Herevpon it followeth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo ſoon as euer a man ſwarueth from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of God, in any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Now when me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come to make laws, to eſtabliſhe the lawes and worſhip of God in any kingdom? let them be the wiſeſt, and the lernedeſt, and the moſt Godly in the whole world: Let the multitude of them be very great:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:10166:28"/> Let their whole purpoſe and care be to ſet foorth no law, but that which in euery reſpect is holy. Yet becauſe God onely hath this glorye to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutelye perfect in wiſedome and knowledge: it muſt needes be graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that ſome imperfection maye be in their lawes, For it is incident vnto men for to erre. Put caſe then they in ſome pointes ſwarue from the truth, and it be afterwarde made knowne vnto men whome God doth further lighten: Shall their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence bee tyed therevnto? If they finde Gods worde to goe one waye, and the law in ſome thing an other, which thinke you they oughte to cleaue vnto? Shall they ſaye thus, they were wiſe that ſet foorth the lawe, we will follow them? Is not God then diſhonoured and denyed, when men are preferred before him? Shoulde they not rather obey God then men? Is it then diſobedience when they refuſe a commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of men, becauſe they dare not diſobey God? It is not for any
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10166:28"/> man raſhely and ſtubbornly to reiect lawes: nor in his owne wilfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite to depraue them: but if with a ſober minde, and good conſcience grounded vppon Gods worde, which hee knoweth to bee againſt anye law, he doe with an humble heart refuſe to obey the ſame law: though men call him rebell, yet before God he ſhall bee cleared as an obedient man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>What is al this to the purpoſe? who doth denye any part of that which you ſay. You ſayd that the very mind of our Lawes is, that nothing ſhoulde be, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods word: thereuppon I did inferre, that their offence is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which diſobey them. I thought ye would haue confuted that and haue ſhewed ſomewhat, as ye ſayd, which I doe not yet ſee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>You doe interrupt me, I was comming vnto that point, I am glad yee graunt that the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt men may faile, and that it is no diſobedience in a man that refuſeth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:10166:29"/> to doe a thing inioyned by them, when hee ſeeth it is agaynſt Gods worde. Nowe to the other poynt, you ſay the more Godly the Lawes are, the greater is their offence that diſobeye them: I ſay ſo alſo: but you gather this out of my wordes, when I ſayde, that the minde and intent of our Lawe is, that whatſoeuer is againſt God and his word, ſhoulde bee throwne downe. If men did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer erre, then that ſhoulde alwaies followe which you woulde inferre? But ſeeing they fayle often in ſome poyntes, which onely ſhoote at that in making their laws, to haue them agree with Gods word, it is but a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion which you make. Now marke what followeth vppon this, which you do not conſider: if it fal out that they eſtabliſh ſomething which is againſt the worde, their minde is that the ſame ſhoulde be eſtabliſhed, ſo ſoone as it is eſpied to bee ſo: the more godly they are, the more is their intent that way. Then to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, you ſay the laws of Godly men
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:10166:29"/> are diſobeied. I ſaye it is not their mind if they be godly, that any thing by them ſet down ſhould be obeied, if it be found to be againſt the worde of God. For this were to deny the lawe makers to be godly: to ſay, that what ſoeuer they haue once decreed, they will haue it obeied, be it found to bee agreeable to the trueth, or againſt the trueth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>This is a very vnwiſe ſpeeche, and ſuch as woulde breede al confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For by this means euery priuate man ſhall be a Iudge and controwler of the Law. Againe, the Law-makers cannot ſet down any penalty to be inflicted vppon the breakers of Lawes. For if this be, that the law ſhall bee challenged to be againſt the worde of GOD, and therefore to haue no power, euen by the minde of thoſe which made it: then howe ſhall thoſe which haue executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of laws diſcharge their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>? they can not diſpence with the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of the Lawe: Lawes cannot be diſſolued, but by the ſame autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:10166:30"/> that they were confirmed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Some men take nothing to be wiſelye ſpoken, but that which commeth out of their own mouth, and their confuſed minde i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magineth confuſion where none is. Euery priuate man, that will bee a true Chriſtian, ought to bee ſo well inſtructed, that he know the thinges he doth, are commaunded by God: and if any thing be commanded him by man, which in his owne Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he knoweth to be forbidden by the worde of God, it is not the lawe that ſhall excuſe him in his deed. Do you thinke that this is a good excuſe which Athieſtes make, when they haue liued in two or three Princes dayes, and profeſſed contrary religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to ſay we are priuate men, wee may not iudge of Laws? but we wil demaunde, are priuate men to bee Iudges and controwlers of Lawes? ſurely in that ſence which you ſpeak, they are not, for it is a very diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thing, that euerye priuate man ſhoulde bee an open reproouer and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:10166:30"/> controwler of Laws, much leſſe may priuate men take vppon them to be reformers. But thus farre a priuate man may go, for the keeping of his owne Conſcience pure, he is to iudge of Laws, and humbly to ſubmit him ſelfe to the penalty, where hee ſeeth, he may not obey, and for the other difficulty which you make, is not the penalty againſt ſuch as do contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly, maliciouſly, and wilfully, deſpiſe and breake Lawes. Doe not the wiſe Law-makers preſuppoſe ſuch executors of Iuſtice, as ſhall be able to diſcerne, whether it be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and ſtubbornly that refuſall is made, or vppon good grounde of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? I would to God it were not, that ſome executors of Iuſtice, did rather come nigher the breaking of their othe, by turning the edge of the Lawe againſt ſuch as it meant moſte of all to fauour and cheriſhe: and the backe towards thoſe whom it purpoſed to cut downe, and that greeuous corruptions were not clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked &amp; couered with pretence of law.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:10166:31"/>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>If yee can not prooue this, yee are worthy to ſmart for it. I doe not thinke there bee any ſuch executors of Laws. The Iudges in the Commonwealth, they be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and wiſe, and as for eccleſiaſtical gouernours, they were neuer more graue and learned, they bee farre from cloking and couering any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, as you ſay, with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Lawe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>I will not meddle with the ciuill Magiſtrates, or with their doinges. But this I will ſaye for Eccleſiaſticall Iudges, that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible corruptions paſſe thoroughe theire Handes: Yea, ſuche and ſo many, that if it pleaſe not GOD in his greate mercy to looke vppon vs, they will lay waſte the Church, and hazard the common wealth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>Ye doe but ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and accuſe falſely: the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes are they which deſtroye the Churche and Common wealthe: they are the Vipers which gnawe oute the Bowelles of theire owne
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:10166:31"/> Mother.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>It is an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye matter barelye to affirme or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye: the worſt men of all (as the ſcribes &amp; Phariſees) did accuſe our Sauioure Chriſte, and ſayde he was a naughty man, affirming that them ſelues were good men. The Pope and his Shauelinges did cry oute vppon <hi>Luther,</hi> and all other true Seruauntes of GOD, calling them Heretiques, vſing alſo that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpeeche which you doe, that they were Vypers, gnawing oute their Mothers Bowelles: But were theſe thinges prooued? no more ſhall you euer bee able to conuynce thoſe whome yee accuſe, nor to iuſtifye thoſe whome yee commende: the Groſe abuſes and abhominations are ſo manye, and withall ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſte, that hee needeth an impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente Face, that ſhall goe aboute to hide them. Thoſe that do with dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation abhorre the ſame, thoſe are Puritans, &amp; preciſe fooles. I will not do as you do, barely affirme or deny.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:10166:32"/> But I wil ſhew from point to point, that which I affirme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>I am as able to prooue any thing that I haue ſaid, as you are to prooue yours, &amp; more able, or elſe I woulde be ſory, ſhewe you what yee can againſt your bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, powre out all your poyſon, and giue me leaue to ſpeak but the truth of thoſe whome you like ſo well: it were good, if men would put on qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et mindes, and not be giuen to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>As men are to bee moſt ſtudious of peace, and to put on quiet mindes: ſo ought they alſo to ſtriue and contend for the maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of Chriſtes kingdome, when they ſee it troden downe, vnleſſe they will ſhew themſelues vnfaithfull to the Lorde: but begin, and ſay what yee can againſt theſe odious Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, and afterward giue mee leaue alſo, to tell yee that which I knowe will not pleaſe yee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>I ſee your ſpeeche doth tend to this iſſue, to prooue who
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:10166:32"/> are the Sciſmatikes, and who do the miſchiefe in our Church, the chiefe Prelats or the Preciſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? I like wel that there ſhold be reaſons &amp; proofes, and not bare affirming, and deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. I will ſit and heare, I pray yee proceed as yee did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>The Puritanes are the vileſt men that be, not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to liue in a common wealth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſedicious and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and make ſtrife among the people: yea they teach men to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient. I thinke this is ynough a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte them, if they had no other faultes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>For the terme Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritane, I doubt not but you giue it vnto thoſe, whom it is commonly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto euery where. And that is, if a man haue liued a foule and diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute life, and begin to looke a little towards the feare and ſeruice of god: By and by, O ſir you are become a Puritan. If God haue any Church or people in the land, no doubt the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle is giuen them. And therefore no
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:10166:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> doubt, Sathan taught this Rethorik to the firſt deuiſer therof againſt men in oure time. But let the name goe. In deed that which yee ſaye is ynough againſt them, and a great deale to much if it were true. Let vs haue it prooued. What example can yee bring in anye one place of this land where any ſedicion hath beene mooued by theſe men? Shew by the effect in ſome one place, that which yee doe ſo boldly charge them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>What neede I bring any particular, or name anye one place, when the thing is ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall? Doe not the people flocke after them euerye where, out of manye Townes, ſomtimes ſeuen miles off? If this be not diſordered and a ſedici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing, I know not what yee wil take to be ſedicious. Is it not a facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing, that the people are affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to ſome men, and care not for hearing other? Is the worde of God better out of one mans mouth, then of an other? No, no, they make the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:10166:33"/> people fantaſticall, it is but a vaine humour in them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Yee ſaye the thing is ſo generall that yee need not ſtand vpon particulers. And for proofe yée ſaye, doe not the people flocke after them euerye where? What doe they flocke after them to make a tumult, or to commit any ſedicious fact? your owne wicked conſcience doth know, that it is to no ſuch purpoſe, but to be inſtructed in the worde. But it is a diſorder, that men ſhould come ſeuen miles to a ſermon. Are not theſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full daies, wherein a multitude haue euen as it were conſpired togeather to famiſhe and ſterue the people of God. The moſt places haue no tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching at home, and they will not ſuffer them to ſeeke abroade, but would keepe them ſtill in ignorance and blindneſſe: and vnder pretence of order, their ſoules muſt periſhe. Yee doe euen as the Prieſtes and Phariſies did againſte Chriſte and his Apoſtles. For when he taught, the people were as ſheepe without
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:10166:34"/> a ſhéepeheard, and therefore flocked out of all quarters to heare him. And when they deliuered him vnto <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> they accuſe him as a ſedicious perſon, which mooued or ſtirred vp the people, teaching through all <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye,</hi> beginning at <hi>Galile,</hi> euen vnto that place. <hi>Luke. 23. verſe. 5.</hi> Thus Chriſt was ſedicious, becauſe the people flocked to heare him. Me thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth you and ſuch as you are, ſhould bluſh when ye make the ſame accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation that the Prieſtes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies did againſt Chriſt. Came it from the father of lies in them? Who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it from in you? <hi>S. Paule</hi> carried abroad the glorious Goſpel: the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple flocked to his preaching where he came, and were inſtructed in the way of life. And what ſaith the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator <hi>Tertullus,</hi> beeing the mouth of the high Prieſte and the Elders be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Felix,</hi> againſt <hi>S. Paule</hi> for this matter <hi>Act. 24. ver. 5. Certainely we haue found this man a peſtilent fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and which mooueth ſedicion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the Iewes thorough the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:10166:34"/> whole world.</hi> Men may ſee, that this is no new practize of Sathan, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the Preachers of the Goſpell to be ſedicious. When Chriſt Ieſus him ſelfe, and his bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> could not be free from this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, who ſhall looke to eſcape? But you colour the matter and ſaye, the people are fantaſticall and facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, addicted to heare ſome, and not otherſome, according to their vaine humor. With this accuſation of the people, yee beare your ſelfe in hande yee haue wonne the fielde. But who doth not ſee (that hath anye iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) how the people are ſo ſcanted of teaching, that if hee be a man of good life, they will goe a great waye to heare him, though he bee but a meane Preacher. It is true in deede which you ſay, they care not for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſome. For why? they teach ſo that a man can be neuer the better for them. Others are of ſuch euill life, that they eſteeme not their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, for what power can it haue? Some will vtter ſuch lyes and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:10166:35"/> againſte others euen out of the pulpit, that euery man may ſee their falſhood. Call yee this a fantaſticall humor in the people, when they care not for hearing ſuch?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>Yee deale vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitably and vnchriſtianly, (I tell yee plainely) in making any compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon betweene vs, and the Prieſtes and Phariſies which went againſte Chriſte and his Apoſtles: theſe doe profeſſe Chriſt as well as your ſelfe. And where as yée woulde excuſe the people: I know they are fantaſtical, &amp; euen to pleaſe their humor, they will heare but who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they like: ſuch a man hath the ſpirit, let vs heare him: ſuch a man hath not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite we care not for him: ſuch a man is a ſound Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, where preacheth he? As for ſuch and ſuch there is no edifiyng in their ſermons, they cannot conuert men,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>I compare the facts and not the men, and if you can ſhew ſuch difference therein, let it be ſéene. If a man reprooue an open and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt ſin in any of you, by and by it
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:10166:35"/> is vncharitably done. In the meane time in your ſelues it is verye good charity, to vtter what yée luſt againſt thoſe whom yee can not detect. And for the people in making choyſe of thoſe which teach: for thoſe reſpectes which you mention, are you a deuine and not aſhamed to open your mouth againſt that? Haue yee loſt all ſence of religion, or do your corrupt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons carry yée againſt your conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? I pray yee do not the true Preachers preach by the power of Gods ſpirite? As <hi>Saint Paule</hi> ſpeaketh of his owne preaching 1. <hi>Cor. 2. ver. 4.</hi> Do yee i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine that euerye one which prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth doth come with this power? No, you know full well there be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>méet preachers. Is not I pray yée, the vſe of preching to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uert mens ſouls? Do yée thinke God hath not his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers whom he ſetteth about this buſineſſe? Or doe yee thinke that all kinde of preaching doth conuert ſoules? You know there are ſome which haue ſmall ſkil, how to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter wholſom food vnto mens ſoules,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:10166:36"/> which can occupy a pulpit an howre or two with fine tales and Fables, and pretie ieſtes to make the people laugh: ſurelie he bewraieth him ſelfe to be a groſſe Dunce, which findeth fault with the people in theſe things, it argueth that he neuer knew what it was to haue his owne ſoul conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>Naie, why do ye not ſpeake of thoſe that preache the Lawe, and doe nothing but thunder, and terrifie mens Conſciences, and bring them into diſpaire: they ſhould preach Chriſte and bring the glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the Goſpell to comfort men: this maketh ſtrife among the people, and maketh them factious: for one is readie in euerie thing to controwl a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, yee may not do this, yee may not doe that: this is againſte Gods commaundementes: in this ye ſinne: &amp; ſo where ther was loue and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and good Neighberhood before, nowe there is contention and part-taking, this is the Fruite of theire preaching euery where, &amp; yet forſooth
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:10166:36"/> theſe men are they, which doe moſte good: theſe are they which conuerte mens ſoules: this is a wicked preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and as I ſayde before, ſo I ſay ſtill, they be ſeditious.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Our ſauiour Chriſt did preach both the Law and the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, <hi>Math. 5.</hi> And ye may ſee his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles did euery where: the Law is the rule of righteouſneſſe, expreſſing the holy and pure wil of God. When it is preached and expounded, men by it come to the ſight of themſelues: and the more they vnderſtande the depth and pureneſſe of the Lawe: the more they eſpy their owne vncleanneſſe, curſedneſſe, and miſerye: and ſo are forced to renounce themſelues, and to cleaue vnto Ieſus Chriſte. Before they come to this, they can feele little ſweeteneſſe in the Goſpell, but are as men which are whole, and therefore neede not the Phyſician: and for this cauſe the Lawe is to bee preached ſtrictly. And againe, when men are brought to the knowledge of their owne nature, and alſo to the faith in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:10166:37"/> Chriſt, then are they to walke in all obedience vnto God. They muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce and forſake vngodlines and worldly luſtes, and liue ſoberly, righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſlye, and Godly in this preſent world. <hi>Tit. 2.12.</hi> The law is the rule to ſhew the euill which we muſt eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew, and the good which we muſt follow. And in this reſpect alſo, the lawe is continually to be vrged. If men preach nothing but the lawe, to thunder and to terrifie mens conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, &amp; to bring them into diſpaier, &amp; ſhew them not the comforts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they do euil. But you do falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſlander the Godly Preachers, and maintaine a very wicked &amp; horrible opinion, which is, that the law ſhold not be preached. And therfore out of many pulpits, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may heare theſe voyces: O theſe Preciſians &amp; Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans they preach the law. The law is aboliſhed, &amp; muſt not now be preched. And then ſome great <hi>Rabbi</hi> ſtandeth glorying, as it were in contempt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, I preach the Goſpell, and this I do euery where. We come &amp; intreat &amp;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:10166:37"/> beſéech yée. Theſe fellowes that do ſo tauntinglie reprooue yee, are not ſent of god: they be not white doues which come from God, but blacke Rauens which come from Hell, good people do not heare them, when they preach thus. Thus they flatter the people in their ſins. This is a moſt filthy ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of mens ſoules vnto deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For vnder the colour of preaching the Goſpell, that all are ſinners, and ſhall be ſaued by Chriſte, they do vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie aboliſhe ſanctification, ſo they ſay they beleeue in Chriſte, it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, howſoeuer they liue in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and all kinde of vngodlineſſe, their conſcience muſt not bee trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: and I pray ye what is the cauſe that they teache thus? they are of a looſe and diſſolute life them ſelues, and therefore they beare with the wickedneſſe of the people, that they may beare with them. But you ſhew a reaſon why the Lawe muſt not be preached: it cauſeth ſtrife and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention among the people, and why? forſoothe when the Lawe is taught,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:10166:38"/> then euery man can eſpy when his neighbour doth ſinne, and then will admoniſh and reprooue him, and when he can not abide it, there gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth ſtrife, and part-taking. Are not men commaunded to admoniſh and reprooue one another when they doe amiſſe. <hi>Math. 18.</hi> verſe <hi>15?</hi> Are not thoſe men to be counted very vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which refuſe to be reprooued? yea are they not become brutiſhe, which when they are admoniſhed for foule ſins, they are at defiance with thoſe that admoniſh them, &amp; then cry out, there is no loue? men muſt flatter them, and bee partakers with them, in all their abominable vices, which we are commaunded to haue no fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhippe withall: but rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue them. <hi>Ephe. 5.</hi> ver. <hi>11.</hi> or elſe all loue is gone: and are not thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſeducers, and falſe Prophetes, which nouriſhe vngodlie men, and harden them in this euill? and like deepe Diuines they crie out, where theſe Puritans are, there is contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I thanke God all my Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:10166:38"/> are at vnitie and loue together, vſing good Neighberhood one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, except it be two or three pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe fooles, which will not do as their honeſt Neighbours do: and let a man looke vppon their Pariſhioners, and hee ſhall finde no knowledge of God among them, but all wicked vices, in which they loue and agrée togeather: their liues and the liues of their tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers are alike, and this is the thing they glory of: a curſed vnitie and a wicked loue, which is in the fleſhe, and yet thoſe that ſeeke to bring men from theſe vices are ſeditious and do hurt, becauſe vngodlie men can not abide the lighte, but doe raiſe vp con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>Yee ſhewe your ſelfe more and more to be vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, euen as all the pack of yee are, to crie out againſt your brethren, and your betters, that they deſtroie mens ſouls, that they be ſeducers, and falſe Prophetes: how will you bee able to prooue that they ſeduce, or that they be like the falſe Prophetes? this doth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:10166:39"/> ſhew what ſpirit yee be of. Yee haue taught your tonges to ſlander. Such as you, doe bewitch the people, and are falſe Prophetes, a company of Aſſes and dolts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>When other men ſpeake the truth, they be vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but when you do lye and ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and raile, yea euen in the pulpit, Aſſes, dolts, cockeſcombes, cockadod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les (for this is the Rethorike of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of yee) yet you are ſtill charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and graue wiſe fathers. I know it is neceſſarye it ſhoulde be prooued, who are ſeducers and falſe prophets. For this yee ſhall finde, that among the Iewes, thoſe that were falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, did call the true Prophetes ſeducers. This yee may ſee betweene <hi>Ieremias</hi> and the falſe Prophetes. Likewiſe <hi>Mychaiah 1. Kinges. 22.</hi> is counted a falſe Prophet. We ſay the Papiſtes are ſeducers and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. They ſay the like of vs. But the triall is all. And how ſhall we trie this matter? Surely euen by the qualities. Thoſe are the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:10166:39"/> and ſeducers, which deale ſo with the people, as the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes did in the olde time. The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſraell</hi> were meruailous wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked walking in all kinde of vices, deſpiſing the holye worde of God: When the Lorde ſent his Prophetes vnto them, calling vppon them to forſake their wicked wayes, and to tourne vnto the Lorde, threatning the iudgementes and vengeaunce of God vnleſſe they did retourne: The falſe Prophetes laboured as faſt on the other ſide, to flatter them, and to make them beléeue they were in good caſe. The Lord complaineth of them <hi>Iere. 23.14. That they ſtrengthened the handes of the wicked, that they ſhould not retourne euery one from his euil.</hi> And a little after in the ſame Chapiter he ſheweth how. <hi>They ſay vnto thoſe that deſpiſe me, the Lord hath ſayde yee ſhal haue peace: and to euerye one that walketh in the ſtubberneſſe of his owne heart, they ſaye, there ſhall no euill come vppon yee.</hi> Marke well if it bee not ſo
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:10166:40"/> at this day among vs: Wickedneſſe aboundeth moſt horriblely. When the Godly Preachers do vehemently threaten vengeance, vnleſſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne: Are there not by and by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that ſtep vp, and find fault that men ſhould be threatned with Gods iudgements? God is mercifull (ſaye they) we muſt preach the Goſpel. Yée be Chriſtians, all men are ſinners. Yea, they tell thoſe that are drowned in all wickedneſſe, and which deſpiſe the word of God: yee be Chriſtians: yee be honeſt men, and good ſubiects: Thoſe that finde fault with yee, doe iudge, and therefore are deuiliſhe. Is not this to ſtrengthen the hands of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked, that they ſhould not returne from their wickednes: to beare them in hand they be good Chriſtians, and ſhall do well ynough? Looke in <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel chapter 13. ver. 22. They make the heart of the righteous ſad by ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whom I woulde not make ſad, (ſayth the Lord) and ſtrengthen the handes of the wicked, that he ſhould not returne from his wickedneſſe.</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:10166:40"/> Who doth not ſee, that this kinde of falſe Prophet is amonge vs euerye where, which doth in Sermons ſéeke to deface ſuch, as haue care to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the holy word, in ſuch ſort that it can not, but make ſad the heart of euery good man to heare it. And how much are the wicked encouraged and ſtrengthened by ſuch Sermons? Yée ſhall ſee them euen ſkippe for ioye. Here is one (ſaye they) which doth fetch vp theſe Goſpellers, theſe gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Sermons: This is a graue man, this is a learned Doctor. Alſo looke in <hi>Micah Chapter 2. ver. 11. If a man or one that lyeth, propheſie vnto thee, of wine and ſtrong drink, he ſhall be the Prophet to this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> The falſe Prophets ſought that way to pleaſe the wicked belly Gods of the worlde, which were giuen to follow their luſts and pleaſures. And what ſay our Prophets? Yee may go to the Alehouſe and drincke and be merry togeather, yee may daunce, yée may play at Cardes and bowles vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sabboth daye, yee maye recreat
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:10166:41"/> your ſelues, yée haue fréedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt, they ſeduce and bewith men, that do refraine them, as though men néeded to be encouraged to ſuch pleaſures.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrem.</speaker>
               <p>Nay thoſe are falſe Prophets which teach the people diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, and ſuch are theſe Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans: they will not obey lawes, and by their example they teach the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple diſobedience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>There is no doubt but thoſe are falſe Prophetes which teach the people diſobedience. And as for the Puritans, their doctrine and practize is this: That men muſt obey y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higher powers vnder paine of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: but when any thing is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded which is againſt gods word, we muſt obey God rather then men. This doctrin is to be taught and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctized in the daies of moſt Godly and moſt chriſtian Princes. If this be to teach the people diſobedience, I can not tel what to ſay. I feare me, it wil be founde, that manye of thoſe which boaſte and brag of obedience, hauing in their mouth nothing but obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:10166:41"/> obedience, euen as if they were obedience it ſelf, do breake mo laws, &amp; the ſame of greater importance, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they charge ſo déeply: and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame means, gods glory is trode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> down, the Church laid waſt, &amp; mens ſouls deſtroyed, dangerous enemies to the Prince, &amp; ſtate of the common wealth, bred and nouriſhed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>It is the property of yée all, to bee full of accuſations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt others, and eſpecially againſt your betters, this is your deuiliſh ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit, when yee are not able to prooue that which yee ſay. It is greatly to be wiſhed, that there were ſeuere pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for ſuch ſlanderous tongs, which are ſo bolde to finde fault at their pleaſure, and to controll ſuch as be in office &amp; authoritie. For, by this means the people and al are drawne on, to prattle and talke of matters which belong not vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: A lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table caſe, what diſorder is brought in by yee, whereby God is diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, his Church troubled, and mens ſoules deſtroyed, and the Papiſts
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:10166:42"/> bred and nouriſhed, and when al this commeth to paſſe, yee woulde ſhift it from your owne ſhoulders, and laye it vpon others. But all wiſe men do ſee well ynough where the blame is to be layd, and doe lament it. I am loath to ſpend many wordes, let vs heare ſome of theſe things prooued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>The end wil ſhew who be ſlanderers, and who they are which are led with a deuiliſh ſpirit. It greeueth yee ſore that yee are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, eſpecially by the people. Yee wiſhe there were ſeuere puniſhment for ſlaunderers. Why is this, becauſe yee hate ſlaundering? No but yee would not haue any ſo much as whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper of thoſe groſe thinges which are amiſſe in yee. The people muſt be like dumbe Aſſes, they muſt beare all at your handes, and ſaye neuer a word: yea euen when it commeth to the hazarding and looſing of their ſoules. Yee can in no wiſe abide that the people ſhoulde haue anye ſkill in the holye Scriptures, for feare they ſhould eſpy ſomewhat in ſuch as you
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:10166:42"/> be. It is a pitifull caſe (as you think) that the common ſort ſhoulde know, what maner of men Miniſters ought to be, and what they ſhould doe: For now yee cannot faile in your duetie, but euery plaine man is able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll yee by the word of God. If the common people ſhould be in daunger of looſing their poſſeſſions, their goods or their liues, yee would ſay it ſtoode them in hand to ſpeake and to plead hard for themſelues, and it were a great iniurie to denie them to ſpeak: how much more doth it ſtande them in hand thinke yee, when their ſouls are in danger not to hold their peace? You require to haue ſome thing proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of that which I ſpake. Yee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny, but that the feeding of the ſhéep of Chriſt, is one of the waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt matters vnder heauen, &amp; which our ſauiour requireth at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſters, euen as they loue him: For ſo he ſaith to <hi>Peter: Loueſt thou me? Loueſt thou me? Loueſt thou me more then theſe? Feede my lambes, feed my ſheepe, feed my ſheepe. Ioh.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:10166:43"/> 21. ver. 15.</hi> As if he ſhoulde ſaye, my ſheepe and lambes, which I leaue in the world, are ſo deare and preſcious vnto me, that of all loue, I requeſt thee to feed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now becauſe the life of his ſheepe, and tender lambes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the life of thoſe ſoules which he bought with his bloud, doth depende vpon the ſincere food of the worde, in which they are continually to be fed: he hath appointed ſhepheards, which ſhal alwayes attende vppon them, to lead them into the gréene paſtures of the word, and vnto the liuely ſprings of water, and that ſhal defende them from wolues, and other cruel beaſtes which wold deuour them: theſe muſt not be blind guides: theſe muſt not be hierlinges: theſe muſt not be Idoll ſhéepheards, dumb dogs, gréedy dogs, rauening wolues, nor vnſauery ſalt: but faithful diſpoſers of the miſteries of God: wiſe embaſadors of the great king, to open and declare his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels vnto men: paternes &amp; examples of al godlines for others to follow, for ſuch the ſcripture appointeth. According vnto this moſt holy ordinance of god,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:10166:43"/> our law doth require they ſhoulde be learned &amp; godly. Is this ordinance of God, or this law kept among vs? Are there not a rablement of vngodlye &amp; vnlearned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appointed to be guides ouer the flock of Chriſt? Is there not leſſe account made of the ſoules of gods people, then men make of their hogs? Are there not in ſundry places poore ſely creatures which were Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh prieſts, that a man ſhall hardly find any ſo ſimple in all their pariſh, ſuch as coulde hardlye liue: as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing men, banckrupts, &amp; vnthriftes, haue they not knocked at the gate, and bin let in? Tailers, ſadlers, ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, and other handycrafts men that could ſcarce read engliſh before, are they not conſecrated, and become maſters in <hi>Iſrael?</hi> A multitude of ſuch as are idle, and ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not indure to take any pains, but loue to play at bowls, cards &amp; tables a great part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wéek, and to be at the alehouſe drinking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong good fellowes, haue founde the miniſtery y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fitteſt place to ſerue their turne. For their chiefe worke is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Sunday to read an Homely,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:10166:44"/> and then he hath preached as wel as he that ſtudied hardeſt all the wéeke. Are there not drunkerds, adulterers, and men ſpotted with manye foule vices in this holy function? Who are to bee blamed, that Gods name is thus diſhonoured, the Church layde waſte, and mens ſoules deſtroyed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſſe there is ſome fault this way that you ſpeak of: But you and your fellowes deale verye lewdly and wickedly diuers wayes as concerning this matter. For firſt of al, yee blame thoſe which are leaſt to be blamed, that is to ſay, the reuerende Fathers the Biſhops, they can not doe with all, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons do preſent them with commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, if they be not admitted, they will haue their <hi>quare impedit.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, yee are like euil birdes which defile their owne neaſt. If there be ſuch faults in the miniſters, it were your part, euen for the calling ſake, to couer and hide them, and not to blaſe them abroad as your maner is. Thirdly, your vncharitable dealing
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:10166:44"/> is not to be borne when yée wil raile againſt them, calling them dumbe dogges; hierlings, Idol ſheepheardes and I know not what: they be men, they be Chriſtians, they be your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren. If there were any Godlines in yee, yee would not ſo handle them. They haue Wiues and Children, what, woulde yee haue them begge? Surely I thinke yee would. This is your pitifull minde towardes other men. We may ſee what it is when men will ſeeme to be ſo zealous, and yet haue no loue in them. Read the 13 chapiter of the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinths,</hi> and yee ſhall ſee what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count is to bee made of men, though they haue great gifts, and can ſpeak like Aungels, and yet haue not loue. <hi>Loue doth couer the multitude of ſinnes:</hi> But ſuch as you, are ſo farre from couering, that yee make things worſe then they are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>It is well yee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe there is ſome fault that way. I neuer ſpake with any yet, that wold not affirme the ſame. There be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:10166:45"/> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are grown to great impudency, but yet dare not for ſhame ſay other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then you do, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter is ſo eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent this pot hath ſo wide a mouth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yee can finde no potlid good enough to couer it. But yet there want no ſhifts, and excuſes in redineſſe: thoſe are wicked and lewde ſtyll, that finde fault: Firſt, becauſe they blame thoſe, which are leaſt of all to bee blamed: for yee ſay they muſte ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte ſuche as the Patronnes doe preſent: doe yee thinke all men are become ſtarke Fooles, that yee may abuſe them, and make them beleeue what ye luſt? I pray ye who made them miniſters? Doubtleſſe if the Patrons layd the Eggs, yet it muſt bee confeſſed, that the Byſhops haue hatched the whole broode of theſe vntimely Byrdes. If they at the firſte offended of ignoraunce, why haue they not lamented this horrible and dreadfull ſinne, and ſought redreſſe? If the Diuell him ſelfe ſhoulde bee conſulted withall, to knowe which were the readieſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:10166:45"/> way, to throw down y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel: I think he woulde ſay this if he ſhould chuſe: I ſuppoſe hee woulde ſende a greate number of thoſe that are alreadye ſent, they ſhall neuer bee able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence this foule iniurie, done to Gods people. Secondlie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachers are like birdes as you ſay, that defile there own neſt, becauſe they rebuke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſins of the miniſtery. Ye know not how far this reacheth, &amp; againſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſhoote this bowlt. Did not the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets reprooue the wickednes of the prieſts? did not our ſauior Chriſt lay open y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quailities of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcribes &amp; pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees? Did not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles paint out wicked teachers in their colours. It is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> part of Gods ſeruants to rebuke vngodlines, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoeuer they finde it. The calling of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtery is an high calling: for they are in Chriſtes ſtead to exerciſe that office, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he him ſelf did whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he liued vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth. They are put in truſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſouls of men, which are the price of his bloud: but yet it doth not followe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for this cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſake their vices are to be couered
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:10166:46"/> It is a vile ſpeech. For the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and preſcious the calling is, the leſſe are they to be borne withall, becauſe they diſhonor and deface the ſame. Who will eſteeme the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of the Goſpell to be ſo high and excellent an office, or to be of anie waight, when he ſhall ſee the verie riffraff of the people, worſe then <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboams</hi> Prieſtes taken in, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted as meete men? Are ſuch fit to ſucceed the Lord Ieſus, and to haue the charge of ſoules? How fearefull ſhall their reckoning be before the high Iudge, that haue put them in, and maintaine them? Doe they not diſhonour the Sonne of God, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer repent for it? Are not their harts hardened, and blinded in this beaſtly ſinne? Yee ſaye moreouer, that it is vncharitable dealing to raile vppon them, and to call them dumb dogges, Idoll ſheepheardes, hierlinges, and ſuch like. Was the prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable, or did he raile, when hee called the idle vnſkilfull Prieſtes, dumbe dogs? Or when he called the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:10166:46"/> couetous Prieſtes that ſought after their owne gaine, greedie Dogges, <hi>Chap. 56. ver. 10?</hi> Is this vnlawfull now, which was lawfull then? Our ſauiour faith they be theeues &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers which were before him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is the doore, <hi>Iohn. 10.</hi> Al that he ſendeth come in at the doore. Thoſe whom he ſendeth not (as in deede he ſendeth none but ſuch as are fit) may well be called theeues and murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers. For they take the hier &amp; deſtroy the ſoules of men. When they haue ſhewed repentance for theſe grieuous ſinnes, they may be eſteemed as bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and Chriſtians. They haue Wiues and children, would yée haue them beg? A pitiful caſe. But I praie yee, is it not a thing much more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, that ſo manie thouſandes of ſoules ſhoulde periſhe, becauſe ſome may not beg. Yée are euen made for this life, and can ſee no further. But why need they beg, let them to their occupation, if they be ſtrong, if not, let them be relieued. You that are ſo charitable and pitiful vnto the Idoll
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:10166:47"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:10166:47"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:10166:48"/> miniſters, which haue done ſo much hurt, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wold think ye would haue a ſinguler care of ſuch as haue pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully labored in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren beg not: ſtil ye call for loue, that couereth the multitude of ſins. Loue doth couer ſins where repentance is, &amp; doth forget them, but our Sauiour willeth to reprooue him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> offendeth, &amp; if he repent not when it is ſhewed to the church, he muſt chunt him as an heathen man: but you would haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue, which ſhould ſhake hands with al kind of vngodlines, &amp; bear with it. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture ſpeaketh of loue, doth nothing at all make for your turne, ſéeing it is to hate a man, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one ſeeth him walk in ſinn,<note place="margin">Leuit. 19.17.</note> and doth let him alone, and not reprooue him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>Yée ſay we haue ſhiftes in a readines. We haue them not ſo readie as you haue your wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and diuiliſhe accuſations. You might vſe better and more ſeemelye ſpéech; but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your mouth doth ſpeake out of the aboundaunce of the heart. Such as yée are, ſuch are your words
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:10166:48"/> You woulde make men beleeue that the Deuill him ſelfe coulde do little worſe, for the chuſing of miniſters. Let the world iudge who haue moſt to do with the deuil, &amp; who beſt ſerue his turne: this doth bewray what ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit yee are of. They be more learned; wiſe, and Godly, againſt whome yee ſpeak, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are meet to be iudged, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trolled by ſuch as you. If there be ſo great offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted in making mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, as you ſay there is: yet it is not the part of inferiors to meddle &amp; to find fault with their gouernors, it is a ſaucines in them, they are not to reforme, the redreſſe muſt be publike authority. When ye cry out againſt the poore miniſters calling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dumb dogs, &amp; ſo deal vnchriſtianly &amp; vnbro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> is your de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Can ye tell what maner of men they were who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he called dumb dogs, &amp; greedy dogs? ye wil follow <hi>Iſay</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet &amp; bee like him, haue you his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite? Why do yee not admoniſh pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatly, &amp; ſo yee ſhoulde doe leſſe hurt, &amp; ſhew your ſelues more charitable?
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:10166:49"/> Is not the calling brought into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, when the miniſters are open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defaced? Are not mens infirmities therefore rather to be couered, and ſpared, then that ſhould happen? Yee do more hurt that way with one ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, then ye are able to do good with an hundreth: For yee doe not onelye make the miniſterie to bee deſpiſed, but alſo make thoſe to be euil thoght of which made them, and bring the people into vnquietneſſe. For how can they tel when they ſee the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſtriue, what to beleeue, or what to follow? Againe, when thoſe are lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle eſteemed, which are in counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and honour, how ſhal the reſt of the miniſterie be eſteemed? yea, how ſhal the Goſpel it ſelfe be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med? Thus do you marre al vnder a pretence of zeale in reproouing ſinne. Yee are the moſt vnprofitable of al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Church: and therefore the firſt that are to be cut off.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>If thoſe accuſations be wicked and deuiliſh, which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt moſt foule and monſtrous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:10166:49"/> for the defence of the cauſe of Chriſt: then are mine wicked and deuiliſh. But how wicked and deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe a thing is this, that he which findeth fault with that which God doth manifeſtlye condemne in his worde, is counted wicked and deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: but he which is a falſe accuſer, in defence of anye corruption, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame man is alowed. <hi>Wo be to them that call good euill, and euill good: dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe light, and light darkneſſe. Ieſ. 5.</hi> Hath not God ordained, that faithful and wiſe ſheepeheardes ſhal feed his flocke, and defende them from the wolfe, and bring them to life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting? Doth not the worde of God ſhew, that where ſuch are wanting the flocke doth periſh, and goe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction? Doe you thinke then, there can be any readier way for the deuil to throw downe the Goſpel, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the church, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to famiſh mens ſoules? By what way are men led to Hell more readily, then to be left in their blindnes, and in their ſins? Is not the readieſt way vnto this, to ſet
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:10166:50"/> blind guides, and ſuch as may leade the people vnto all vngodlines? Can the Deuill if he did make, and ſende foorth miniſters, find worſe vpon the earth, then ſundry are? I thinke if he will haue worſe, he muſt bring them from hell. The world ſeeth this, and doth wonder. The lord God open the eyes of thoſe which made them, that they may ſée, and be aſhamed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. But you ſay, if there be ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in making miniſters, yet infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours are not to meddle, it is a ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines in them, it is publique authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that muſt refourme. No deubt it is publique authoritie that muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme. But what then? Are the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Gods word when they pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe his will, become ſawcie? Shall the great God, whoſe meſſengers they are, be diſhonoured, his church laid waſte, and his people deſtroyed, becauſe they muſt reſpect perſons? Doe not you know that God ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his ſeruauntes euen vnto high and low, to reprooue them when they do amiſſe? You ſhew your ſelfe to be
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:10166:50"/> proud and ſawcie againſt God, that yee will haue his worde giue place vnto mortall men. Were not the moſt of the Prophetes inferiour per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and yet they reprooued openly the high Prieſtes, when they did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, and ſpared not any of what degrée ſoeuer? The Pope and his Biſhops can chalenge no more, then to doe what they luſte, and that without controlement, of anye but them ſelues, which affirme that the power to redreſſe thinges is onely in their hands. We may not giue thoſe titles vnto euill miniſters that the Prophetes in the ſcriptures do. And why? Becauſe we haue not the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of the Prophetes. This is as deepe deuinitie as any that yee could dig out of the bottome of a Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill. I pray yee what Spirite ſhal the Preachers of the Goſpell be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with all, if not with that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Spirite of God, which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſpake by? Is there an other holye Ghoſte? In deede the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes had great and extraordinary
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:10166:51"/> giftes of the ſpirite to doe that which we cannot. But doth it therefore fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that we may not reprooue ſin as they did? It is one principall part of the duetie of the Teachers, where in they are to follow the ſteps of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Prophets. The offence is publike and open euerye where, and yet men muſt be reſtrained fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king publikely againſt it. But you ſhew diuers great hurtes that enſue by open reproouing this matter. The miniſtry, yee ſay is brought into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt by this meanes, and it were much better mens infirmities were couered, then that ſhould happen. As though the true miniſterie coulde be brought into contempt, by reprouing that which is corrupt? It ſhoulde ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee conſidered, that it ſhoulde bring them into contempt with god, and all Godly men, if they ſhould not reprooue them. For then they might ſéem to ſhake hands with them, &amp; to alow their vngodlines, &amp; not to care how this high calling be defiled by laying it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vile perſons, they might
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:10166:51"/> alſo be thought not to pity y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules of men? do not you ſée, that if fools which are baſe, beggerly, and vnciuil, and of lewd conuerſation ſhoulde be made Iudges, it woulde be the greateſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to the office that might bee? The hurt reſteth not you ſhew, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facing the miniſtry, but reacheth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe that made them. In deed it is their diſcredite which made them, And that is the cauſe why the true teachers are hunted and toſſed about. For if they preach againſt the inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie of any of the miniſtery, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their lewde life which all ſee? Then they poſt vp, and carry newes. My lord, ſuch and ſuch preach againſt your Lordſhip. I warrant yee thoſe teachers ſhal haue as much a doe to defend them ſelues, as to teach their people. But this is that which doth marre all, when thoſe that be of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, are by any meanes brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to contempt: For they doe counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce the Goſpell and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtry, and were it not for them, the Goſpel ſhould be little eſteemed, nor the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:10166:52"/> thereof. Alaſſe, is the glorye of the Goſpel no greater, nor the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the miniſterie no more, but that they muſt ebb and flowe, with the worldly honour and glorye of ſome men. How vnwiſe do yee take our Sauiour Chriſte to be, that he layde his glory a ſide, and tooke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him the ſhape of a Seruaunt,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.6.</note> that he might bee a miniſter of the Goſpell? How vnſkilfull was he in chooſing ſuch ſimple men to be his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, as hadde no glorye to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce the matter? Hee might haue come with greater pompe. But he ſayeth, <hi>My kingdome is not of this worlde, Iohn. 18. verſe 36. Saint Paule</hi> ſayeth, <hi>The weapons of our warfare are not carnall, but mightye in God. 2. Corinth. 10.</hi> If that were a good reaſon which you make, then were it a ſpeciall matter, that there ſhoulde be as great glorye and pomp in the miniſterie as euer the Pope and his Cardinalles had. For the ſame reaſon ſet them vp at the firſte. No, no, the dignitie and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:10166:52"/> of the miniſterye doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the power of Gods ſpirite in them. <hi>1. Corinth. 2. verſe 4.</hi> This ſpirite doth alwayes cauſe thoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to be had in great reuerence in whom he ſpeaketh, although they be neuer ſo baſe in outwarde appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, as <hi>Paule</hi> was. Contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, let a miniſter of the Goſpell gliſter in Golde, and ſit ſo high in glory and power, that his feet be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the heades of Emperours and Kinges, yet neuertheleſſe hee ſhall be vile, and euen ſtincke in the noſtrels of men, beeing voyde of the power of the ſpirite, which is the furniture of a right miniſter. For God ſayth, <hi>I wil honour thoſe that honour me, and they that deſpiſe me, ſhalbe deſpiſed. 1. Sam. 2. ver. 30.</hi> And what ſayth the Lord by the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> vnto the Prieſtes <hi>Chapi. 2. verſe. 9?</hi> Doth he not tell them, that becauſe they departed out of the waye, hee had made them deſpiſed, and abiect vnto all the people. Then yee ſee it is God that bringeth ſuch as bee of great
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:10166:53"/> dignitie into contempt, becauſe they degenerate: yee ſaye the people are vnquieted, becauſe they can not tell whom they maye beleeue. It is a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue in theſe dayes beene kept in ſuch blindneſſe, that they can not trie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Spirits,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.1. Iohn. 10.</note> nor are not able to know the voyce of Chriſt, or at the leaſt can not ſee who walke after the worde of God, and who doe not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>I graunt it is a readie way to deſtroye the Church, where mens ſoules are famiſhed. Who goeth about any ſuch matter? God be thanked, the worde was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more plentifully ſet foorth. They need not famiſh, for where they haue not a Preacher, yet they haue the Scriptures read vnto them in their owne language: they haue Prayers and Homelyes, as good as anye can bee made. There bee manye good Bookes, they maye reade, or heare them read: but ſuch as you, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne reading, are thoſe that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh mens ſouls, if any do. Yee are
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:10166:53"/> vngodlie, and vtter enimies to mens ſouls, when ye wil lead them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Scriptures vnto your expoſitions: as though they could profite by hearing and reading youres, and not by the reading of the Byble. Where ther be blinde guides and hirelings, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple periſh, no man doth deny that: you ſay many of the miniſters bee ſuch, I ſay they bee not: for they ſet out the word &amp; Sacraments, though not by their owne learning. But let it be graunted, that ſome of them bee blinde guides, yet the people neede not periſh, for there bee others that watch ouer them, beſides the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the Byſhops and Archdeacons: theſe are not blinde, but haue their ſight better then the Puritans. O, but theſe can not ſuffice, with al their learning and Godlineſſe to guid the people, and to keepe them in good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but forſooth euery congregation muſt haue one to preach vnto them: this were good, but where will yee haue them? if ye can finde men, wher are the liuings that ſhall maintaine
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:10166:54"/> them? will yee haue Preachers to liue with tenne pounde, or twentie pounde a yeare, ſurelie yee are verie Doltes, and woulde haue ye knowe not what. I woulde you coulde ſee your owne follie, which verie Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren doe ſée, that yee mighte bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, the people are well if yee coulde let them alone, and are come from Poperie. But if they bee not Puritans, by and by yee enter into iudgement againſt them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them to bee Athieſts and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, yea, to bee reprobates, and for this cauſe yee crie out, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple periſh, mens ſoules are fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and murthered for lacke of preachers: are not the people (which you ſaie periſh and go to deſtruction) Chriſtians? do they not at their ende call vpon God, confeſſe their ſinnes, and hope to be pardoned by the death and bloudſhedding of Chriſte? howe then dare you bee ſo wicked and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous, as to iudge of them, that they be damned? Will you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Gods ſecretes? I thinke bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:10166:54"/> of ſuch honeſt poore men, which are dutifull ſubiectes, and liue quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, thogh they haue no teaching, then of ſuch as you: the ſtate of our church would be better, if all were ſuch, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there ſhould be more quietnes, then there is now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>If euer there were anie time, in which the words of our ſauiour Chriſte were verified, when he ſaith, <hi>If it coulde be posſible, the elect ſhould be deceiued,</hi> it is nowe: there be ſuch goodlie ſhewes and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours made and ſet vpon matters, to holde the people contented in their ignoraunce: for what is proclaymed nowe? and vnder what doe thoſe that deſtroie the Churche, ſhrowde them ſelues, but the Goſpell, the peace of the Church, obedience, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, grauitie, and Godlineſſe: All theſe are moſte excellente thinges, and therefore when they come but for a cloake (as they doe vnto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny which haue not the vſe and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of them) the daunger is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greater. Yee ſay the people neede not famiſh
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:10166:55"/> the goſpel is ſo plentifully ſet foorth? what preached? no that is but heere and there. How then? that which is as good as preaching: the ſcriptures are read in their owne tongue, with homilies and prayers, as good as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny can be made. There be alſo many good bookes: yea ſyr, but what ſayth the holy Apoſtle. <hi>1. Cor. 1. ver. 21.</hi> he ſaith, <hi>It is the pleaſure of God to ſaue thoſe which beleeue by fooliſh preaching.</hi> Wil ye not giue the Lord leaue to ſaue that way which it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him? or will ye preſcribe him an other, that ſhal be a wiſer way? <hi>Faith commeth by hearing, and how ſhall they heare without a Preacher? Rom 10. the Prieſtes Lippes muſt keepe knowledge, and they muſt ſeeke the Law at his mouth, for he is the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of the Lord of Hoſtes. Mala. 2. verſ. 6. Thoſe thinges which thou haſte heard of me among many wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle vnto <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy) the ſame commit vnto faithfull men, which may bee meete to teach others. 2. Tim. 2. verſ. 2.</hi> You ſée then,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:10166:55"/> Gods pleaſure is, to worke fayth and to ſaue by preaching: his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce and appointment is, that ſkilfull, wiſe, and godly paſtors ſhall féede his flock: they muſt inſtruct and teach the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the miſteries of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel, and lay open vnto them all the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of God, <hi>They muſt preache the worde and be inſtant, in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, they muſt conuince, reprooue, exhort, with all long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering and doctrine. 2. Timo. 4. verſ. 2. They muſt watch ouer the ſoules of men, as thoſe that ſhall giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count vnto God for them. Heb. 13. verſ. 17.</hi> I pray yee tell mee, can the dumbe Idoles, hirelings, and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men do this? God muſt néeds take men to heauen that way which you deuiſe, although it be flat againſt his owne ordinaunce. God hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to giue his Spirite, with the true miniſterie which hee ſendeth to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh remiſſion of ſinnes in his name, by which ſpirite he conuerteth mens ſoules: will ye therefore binde him to doe the ſame, to a falſe miniſterie?
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:10166:56"/> are yee not aſhamed thus to mocke with GOD, and to abuſe his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? the reproche and ſhame of this will neuer bee done awaie with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Sacrifice or burnt offering. Yee ſay we condemne reading, and ſome of yee are not aſhamed with Braſen faces to affirme it, euen oute of the Pulpit. We exhort and ſtirre vp the people vnto the diligent reading of the Scriptures, and where ſhall a man finde ſo manie Bybles and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamentes in the handes of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſorte, as where thoſe Puritan Preachers (as you tearme them) haue anie while continued? A man would thinck, conſidering howe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt a lye it is, that the Diuel him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe woulde bee aſhamed to vtter it, as I haue hearde ſome of yee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the miniſters ſet foorth the worde and Sacramentes (though it bee not by their owne learning) you ſaie they bee no blinde guides nor hirelings, what manner of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out is that when the people do not receiue inſtruction? they doe as
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:10166:56"/> much as lieth in them prophane the worde and Sacramentes. But what though there were blinde guids and hirelinges, yet the people are well ynough, they depende vppon the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Archdeacons, which can ſee better then Puritans. Theſe I trowe can ſuffice to keepe the people in order. I pray yee what can they ſee, or what do they ſee? to leade the people to Heauen, or to builde them vp in good order in the fayth? Noe, no, they can ſee that they ſhal be kept in blindneſſe, as they are, but what can they doe vnto thoſe whome they neuer ſaw nor knew? doth there goe ſuch vertue out of a Byſhoppe or an Archdeacon, that it can ſpreade it ſelfe ouer all the Country, euen to ſaue their ſoules, that neyther heare nor ſee them? ſhall the blinde bee ledde by thoſe that neuer come nigh them, or by thoſe that are preſente and take them by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand? for ſhame holde youre peace. Yee confeſſe it were good, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the people were taught euery where, but where will yee
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:10166:57"/> haue ſo many teachers? and if there be men, ye demaund where ther wil be liuinges for them? To the firſt I aunſwere, that the want of Godlie and diligent preachers is to bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the Biſhops: for euen as if they had conſpired the death of the Church, they haue laboured to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and diminiſh them. To goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to put out thirtie or fortie in a ſhire, and then to ſaie, where ſhall we haue preachers, is an odde kinde of queſtion? To fill vp the roomes ſo ſoone as they be voide, with Taylers, and ſeruingmen, or ſuch like, ſo that the learned men in the Vniuerſities not called foorth, do hold ſtil their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhips in Colledges: the yong men therby conſtrained for want of main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tainance, depart from thence before they be halfe ripe, ſome to teach ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, ſome into gentlemens houſes, &amp; manie to pop into the miniſtery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they bee méete to guide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and then to demaund where ſhall wee haue learned men, is alſo verie abſurd? To the ſeconde I aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:10166:57"/> that if Biſhops, Deanes, and, all the fat ones of the Cleargie did not loue their owne bellyes, more then the thinges which are of the Lorde Ieſus: and if they did not eſteeme the pompe, pleaſures, and richeſſe of the worlde, more then mens ſoules, there would be ſuch ſufficiencie of maintenaunce, that if there were fiue Preachers where ther is but one, yet none of them ſhould be ſo bare as to liue with <hi>20.</hi> pounde by the yeare. We read <hi>Actes. 4.</hi> that when the Church was in need, ſuch as had poſſeſſions, ſold them to relieue the bodies of the bretheren that wanted: How much more then ought thoſe, which haue their thouſandes, to imploy and beſtow the ſame to haue the ſoules of men fedde? Mens ſoules do famiſh you ſaye; if it be ſo, it is becauſe in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie places they haue not maintenaunce for a Preacher. I praye yee which of the fedde men, haue deminiſhed their pompe, their richeſſe and pleaſures, which neuer did penyworth of good in the Church, to ſet vp faithfull Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers? What drop of zeale for Gods
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:10166:58"/> glory doth appear in manie of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? But if this ſeeme harde, as it will to worldly minded me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet why haue they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſented y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a number ſhould do nothing but hunt after benefices &amp; prefermentes, and to heap vp liuing vpon liuing, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> portions of fiue or ſix? ſome which are paſt this, &amp; haue put all their treaſure in one bag, will confeſſe this is abhominable: but which of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth ſeek redres. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people be in ſo good caſe as you ſay, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther needeth no redreſſe: For you ſay they be wel, &amp; are come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pope<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry. I maruel to what they be come? they ſay in deed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the pope is naught, but try the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ye ſhal find, that they are ſtuffed ful of popiſh and ſuperſticious opinions which are contrary to the wholſom doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the goſpel. The ſcriptures eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where doe deſcribe true Chriſtians to bee holye and pure, and full of the knowledge of God. And as for thoſe that walke in darkeneſſe, wallowing in all filthie vices, the Lorde denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth vengeaunce againſt them. When the true and faithfull Preachers doe teach men that they can not be ſaued, vnleſſe they tourne from their euill
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:10166:58"/> wayes, ſeeking after the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and walke woorthie of the ſame: and that ſuch as be ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, ſuch as be ſwearers, ſuch as bee couetous, ſuch as be drunkards and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, ſuch as be ignorant deſpiſers of the knowledge of the will of God: fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, ſuch as liue in anie abhominable vices, are not true Chriſtians: by and by like warriers for the Deuils kingdom, ye ſaie we would haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people become Puritans. A man can not ſo ſoone miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like groſe ſins, but ſtraightway: O ſyr, you like none but Puritans. You iudge and condemne men. Howe can you tell who haue faith? Surely if this bee not to ſeduce, to harden, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then men in their wickedneſſe, I know not what is. Might not all this bee ſpoken to the Prophetes of God in olde time by the falſe Prophetes, which did flatter the wicked, euen as ſuch as you be doe now? It woulde make a mans heart bleed to ſee in what caſe mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of people are for want of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and yet you ſay they be wel. The greateſt multitude by manye partes
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:10166:59"/> doe not vnderſtande the Lordes prayer, the ten Commaundementes, or the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the faith, or the doctrine and vſe of the Sacramentes in anye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent meaſure. There be thouſandes which bee men and women growen, which if a man aſke them howe they ſhall be ſaued they can not tell. As for wickedneſſe, in pride, enuie, hatred, &amp; al ſinns y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can be named almoſt, it doth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerflowe, &amp; yet you are not aſhamed to ſay, are they not chriſtians? do they not call vpon God at their ende? This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuinitie of ſome of our great diuines at this day. Let men liue as they luſt in ignoraunce and all abhominations, ſo they call at the laſt, and ſay Lorde haue mercy vppon me, we muſt iudge their eſtate as good as the beſt. As though the Lorde had not ſayde, <hi>Yee ſhall crye and not be heard. Prouerb. 1.</hi> And as though ſuch as know not the faith, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought vp in blindneſſe, coulde of a ſoudden, euen at their pleaſure, pray in faith without doubting. For the Scripture ſheweth that he which doth doubt in his prayer, ſhall obtayne no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:10166:59"/> 
                  <hi>Iames. 1.</hi> Our ſauiour willeth men to ſtriue to enter in at the ſtraight gate, ſhewing that fewe ſhall finde it. If a man maye follow his luſtes, and walke in the blindneſſe of his heart all his life, and then a little calling at the laſt would ſerue: What hardneſſe were in it? When yee tell men God is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, all men ſinne, what ſhoulde yee make your ſelfe more holy then other? Yee ouerthrow all the doctrine of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, and all the precepts which the Apoſtles doe giue for walking wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie the Goſpell. You make the good and the bad in one condition, as though there were no profite to ſerue the Lord, as he complaineth <hi>Malachy. 3.</hi> But wherefore doe great men now a dayes take it ſo grieuouſly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> anye difference of men ſhould be made? Surely I will tell yee the cauſe. They would not haue their treaſon againſt the Church of Chriſt eſpied, when they thruſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them wicked and vnlearned mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters: For they woulde haue men taught, and men vntaught, men Godly and men wicked, all in one account:
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:10166:60"/> that it might not appeare howe they murther mens ſoules. Nay yee like beſt, as yee confeſſe of thoſe that be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt. And why? Becauſe they are quiet. In deed you are leaſt troubled with thoſe which be moſte ignoraunt, for they can not eſpie your dealing. Such as haue knowledge in Gods worde can ſaye, what a wolfe is this? he hath three benefices, and ſetteth a Tailer in one, a drunckard in an other, And how he flaunts it? He doth viſite them once in a yeare, to ſee that they doe him no wrong in his tithes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrem.</speaker>
               <p>If I had authoritie I would puniſh yee ſharply, and make yee carrie a better tongue in your head. For if this may be ſuffered, we ſhall haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie man a controller ſhortly. Yee are the vileſt men that liue, and indeed ſuch as do moſt hurt of all others. Yee are a peſtilent generation, in my iudgement worſe then the Papiſtes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Who could imagine that in this great light of the Goſpell it might come to paſſe, that for ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt ſuch thinges as God doth
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:10166:60"/> flatly condemne in his worde, men ſhould bee counted the vileſt perſons that liue? A peſtilent generation. Worſe then the Papiſtes? For what is it which we condemne in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, but ſuch thinges as the Lorde him ſelfe hath firſt condemned? We crie out againſte ambition, couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, greedines in heaping vp liuings, worldly pompe, idleneſſe, and ſuch like. We finde fault, that vnfit men, both for learning and conuerſation, are ſet to be guides ouer the Lordes people. Doth not the Lorde by his Prophetes and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles reprooue the ſame? And yet if you had authoritie we muſt be ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie puniſhed. All men maye ſee what ſpirite doth poſſeſſe your heart, when you woulde ſharpelie puniſh for reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that, which the Lord him ſelfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooueth. If yee did puniſhe me, all the world ſhoulde ſee that it were for ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt vice. But I know you wil ſay it is not for ſpeaking againſt vices, but for charging ſuch men as are free from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The world were wonderfully chaunged, if theſe vices were not to be
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:10166:61"/> found: and whither they abound among vs, let al men iudge that be indifferent. Then when they be ſpoken againſt, &amp; no particuler men named, but among many, ſome are blamed: why ſhold thoſe which are not guilty take it grieuouſly? Let thoſe wintch which haue galled backs: for they ſay, rub the galled horſe and he will wintch, and ſome Horſe is ſo pitiouſly galled, that if a man come into the Stable, and doe but point to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes him, he will ſnib and take on, for feare the finger ſhoulde touche his backe. Euen ſo play you: for if you had authority you woulde puniſh me ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. We are charged to doe the moſte hurt of all others: ſurely then it is vnto non-reſidents, double beneficed men, i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and ſlow-bellies, vnlearned Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that this hurt is done by vs, for in trueth it is the part which you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, which doth the hurt. Firſt vnto the Lord God, then vnto our ſoueraign Lady and gracious Queene, and laſtly vnto her faithfull ſubiects.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>This is a foule and a ſhamefull ſlander, and in my mind
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:10166:61"/> you woulde bee driuen and forced to make proofe of your wordes, and bee made to recant them. I knowe your ſpeech doth tend euen againſt ſome that are chiefe Miniſters in the Church. It is not meete that inferiour perſonnes ſhoulde ſpeake of them and of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>There ſhall neede no greate inforcement to make me prooue that which I haue ſaide. For if I can not ſhew it to be true, let me looſe my life. My wordes tend againſt thoſe that are guilty, and none elſe, whether they be cheefe Miniſters or otherwiſe: and whereas you ſay that it is not meete, that inferiour perſons ſhould ſpeake of cheefe miniſters and of theire doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: the Pope can challenge no more. The people ſpake of oure Sauioure Chriſt, and he was content they ſhould ſcan his doings. The people did ſpeak of the bleſſed Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp; found fault that he had gone in vnto men vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed and had eaten with them, becauſe he had beene with <hi>Cornelius. Peter</hi> doth not diſdaine, but ſatiſfieth
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:10166:62"/> them concerning his fact. <hi>Actes. 11.</hi> But the Pope and his generation, are ſo highe aboue CHRISTE and his Apoſtles, that they maye not bee ſpoken of. Well againſt whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it bee, I ſayde that the part, which you defende dothe the hurte, vnto God, to oure gratious Prince, and to her true ſubiectes. And nowe I will ſhew ye how. Firſt, by the corrupt miniſterie Gods name is diſhonoured, becauſe his holie ordinance is defiled and brought into contempt: the dignity of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt is abaſed, when ther are put into that office which hee had, and doe repreſente his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſuch as men woulde ſcarce truſt to keepe their Swine. Notable iniurie is done by this meanes alſo, vnto our Queenes moſte excellent Maieſtie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath long time endangered her moſte roiall perſon, by ſtrengthning her enemies. For where the people are kept in blindeneſſe, the Ieſuites can eaſilie worke vppon them, there neede no greate perſwaſions, but to tell the poore ignoraunte creatures,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:10166:62"/> that this is a newe religion, and will not you doe as youre Graundfather, and youre greate Graundfather did? Will you bee wiſer then they? Doe yee think they be damned? they knew not this learning. You may ſee what manner of Goſpell this is, when they make ſuche Miniſters. Was not your Miniſter a Cobler? Was not the Miniſter of ſuch a place an Innekee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vntill he was bancrupt? And thus they maye leade them at theire plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Againe, who is able to reckon vp the manifolde diſorders and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that ſpring from the Dumbe and vngodly Miniſterye? and let a man ſpeake agaynſte any of the ſame abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and diſorders: Shall hee not by and by heare this. O ſir, you will bee wiſer then the Queene and her Counſayl, they allow of theſe things, and will haue it thus. Is not this a ſhamefull iniurye, doone vnto her Maieſtye, and her moſte Honourable Counſayle, when all ſuche matters ſhall bee caſt vppon their ſhoulders?
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:10166:63"/> Furthermore, from whence doth the great aboundaunce of all kinde of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and prophaneſſe among the people ſpring, but from thence that they want inſtruction? and doth not this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunger the ſtate of the prince, and the whole Lande? doth not the Lorde gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly plague whole Kingdomes for ſinne? laſtly the iniury done to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is manifeſt. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, he that keepeth backe his corne, the people doe curſe him. Howe much greater is the wrong, when the breade of life, vppon which their ſoules ſhoulde feede is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them? Thus haue I ſhewed by whome the hurt is done: It might be ſhewed in an hundred thinges, but theſe are manifeſt, and of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos</speaker>
               <p>You and your fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes do the hurt (as I ſaid before) and then ye woulde lay it vpon others. And after ye haue vttered ſome imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then there be an hundred things in which it might be ſhewed. Your tong is not ſo tied, but that it would be wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, if there were ſuch matters. Look
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:10166:63"/> whatſoeuer ye ſay, it muſt goe for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, after ye haue made ſome ſhew in that ye haue deuiſed. Ye are eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the Papiſts: ye haue the very properties of the Annabaptiſtes, and he that ſhall marke the end, ſhall ſee what it will come to, if ye bee let alone. But I pray God ye may bee cut ſhort, and that we may not any further feele the effect of your ſeditious doctrine. I hope ye will be ſeene vnto ſpeedily.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Whether they be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations which I haue vttered, I leaue to the iudgement of ſuch as bee wiſe. I doubt not, but if they be tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly wayed, they ſhall be founde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding waighty. You gather by my ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that I haue no matters: Surely I dare affirm, that he which ſhall take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to vtter al particulers, in ſuch abuſes as are manifeſt, and doe hurt in our Church, had need to do nothing elſe for one whole day, and take the longeſt in the year. Your accuſations againſt vs be ſtale, when ye charge vs to haue conſpired with the Papiſtes, and to haue the properties of the Annabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:10166:64"/> Your own conſciences do witnes that wee are farre from theſe ſortes of men. The Papiſts and Annabaptiſts knowe well enough, that of all other we doe leaſt ſerue their turne. Wee loue the Papiſtes ſo well, that we wiſh there were not a ſhread of their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome left, nor ſo much as one relique of theirs, euer to bee ſeene among vs. The end of all our trauail is, to builde vp the walles of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and to ſet vp the throne of Ieſus Chriſte, our Heauenlie King in the middeſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to bring the people in ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto him: howe ſoeuer <hi>Sanballat</hi> and <hi>Tobiah,</hi> doe accuſe vs, that wee meane to rebell. You pray that we may he cut ſhort, and that yee may not feele anie further the effect of our ſeditious Doctrine. It is the Doctrine of Ieſus Chriſte, and the effect of it which you feare is, to cut downe worldlie pompe, Couetouſneſſe, and idleneſſe in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie. You feare that if it take place, that you muſt parte with two of youre Benefices: Naie, you feare that you ſhall get no higher, there bee manie of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:10166:64"/> yee, which haue layde a Platfourme howe to come vnto wealthe and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. Yee fear that the great roomes will bee little woorth before youre turne come, and that dothe cauſe you to frette and rage againſte the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge of the Goſpell. Yee deuiſe all the fleſhlie reaſons which yee can, to maintaine and vpholde Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Yee beate youre Braynes, and ſpende youre Wittes to deface Gods Ordinaunces, and why doe yee this? forſoothe euen for the Churches ſake, for the peace of the Churche, and for Obedience and good order: Yea, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as muche as <hi>Iudas</hi> had a care for the Poore. It is well ſeene, that if there were not greate wealth and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noures, for which yee contende, yee woulde ſcarce open youre mouthe for ſuche matters, as nowe yee defende as eagarlie as if it ſtood vppon your liues. The Miniſters of the Goſpell muſt alwaies paſſe thorough troubles, but the Lorde Ieſus will looke vnto them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos</speaker>
               <p>There are none ſo
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:10166:65"/> couetous and ambitious as your ſelues: And that maketh yee to grudge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine at thoſe which haue wealth and honour, becauſe yee can not come by it. Yee are loath to bee inferiours, your mindes be ſo proud and ſtately. I know if a man will hearken to all your ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and falſe accuſations, you can hold him a whole day, yea three dayes, and let them be the longeſt in the yeare: but tell but truth, and then a leſſe time wil ſerue well ynough. As I ſayd before, if there were matter it ſhoulde not be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Yee ſay we conſpire with the Papiſtes, but your maner of dealing is ſo like theirs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man would think ye were ioyned together in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of one cauſe. For when <hi>Luther</hi> dealt againſt the pope, by &amp; by, they cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out that it was, becauſe he could not come to that preferment which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. So play you againſt vs, when we reprooue thoſe forenamed vices in the Cleargie. For yee ſay we doe it becauſe we can not abide to be inferiours, and becauſe we can not come to dignitie
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:10166:65"/> and wealth, this wicked ſurmiſe of yours, hath no colour or ſhew of trueth. It is well knowne, that there be not a few, which could as eaſily come to their Benefices as you, if they woulde la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for them, and that might attaine vnto great dignity, if they woulde ſet their minde that way: but they haue learned, that ſuch as bend them ſelues to ſeeke after liuings and promotions, do not ſerue the Lorde Ieſus, but their own bellies. If you could iuſtly charge men, that they had ſought and laboured for dignity, and yet miſſed, then were there ſome cauſe for ye to ſay ſo, but ſeeing it is otherwiſe, me thinketh, if there were but a drop of common ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty in ye, ſuch ſpeech could not be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered: Ye do alſo iump with the papiſts after this ſort, when the Seruaunts of God reprooued the pride of the Pope: then what was the common voice, but that if theſe men bee not looked vnto, haue at Kings next? So now reprooue Ambition and worldly pompe in the Cleargy, and what followeth? Let prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Noble men take heede: theſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:10166:66"/> men will haue a fling at them ſhortly: but bleſſed be GOD, it is well ſeene, that the caſting downe of the Pope, is the exaltation of Princes. For while he ſtandeth like that prowde <hi>Senacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib</hi> King of <hi>Aſhur:</hi> euery <hi>Rabſaka,</hi> yea, euerie one of his Captaines, will take himſelfe to bee, as good as King <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias, Ieſa. 36.</hi> ver. <hi>9:</hi> But let this go. You vrge me to ſpeake of abuſes, and you ſay, that if I ſpeak but the trueth, a ſhort time will ſerue. But I ſay, hee that will declare the corruptions, but of your ſpirituall Courtes, hee maye hold himſelf occupied a good peece of a day, and yet ſpeake but trueth. I know not where a man ſhoulde beginne, or whome he ſhall finde to be the worſt: the Iudge himſelfe or the Scribe, the Proctors or the Summoners: This is ſure, all of them regard nothing but Money. All the whole Court is gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by one rule, but that is a Golden rule. The people maie not ſpeake a worde, for if they doe, they bee Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belles, Rebelles, and ſpeake againſt
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:10166:66"/> the Queenes authoritie: When as in deede the Queenes Lawes are broken, and her Subiectes greatly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>Marke your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges who will, and hee ſhall finde this property in yee, that all your drift is agaynſte authoritie. Nowe the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Courtes come in, great cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions are in them. If it be as you ſaye, it is pitty they ſhoulde ſtande. But it is well ſeene, howe ſoeuer ſuche as you barke agaynſte them, that as they bee appoynted for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Vices, ſo they doe muche good: none repine at them, but ſuch as can not abide to bee puniſhed for their diſorders. If ſome officer doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe at ſome time (as all can not bee good) what reaſon is it that yee ſhould ſo lewdlie accuſe the whole Courte? you make the Iudges, the Scribes, the Proctors and Summoners, all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. If I were an Archdeacon, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall, or Commiſſarie, I would take the lawe againſt ye for a ſlaunder. You ſay al is done for monie, &amp; the Lawes
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:10166:67"/> are broken, and the Queenes ſubiectes are abuſed. I doubt not, but if yee were put to your proofe, yee woulde eate your wordes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>He that will marke, ſhall finde this quality in a number of yee? that a man cannot ſo ſoone ſpeake againſt corruptions and abuſes, in ſuch as abuſe their authority, but ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way yee accuſe him, as one which can not abide to bee vnder anye gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe hee woulde not be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected for his diſorders. You knowe well ynough, that this is a ſhrewde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation to bring men into ſuſpition, cheefely among thoſe whome GOD hath ſet vp in high authority. This is the crafty wilineſſe of the Serpent, that men might be terrified, and made to keepe ſilence, what ſo euer enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be committed. But you ſhall not terrify mee from ſpeaking that of the Spirituall Courtes, which is open and apparent vnto all men: Neyther ſhall yee euer bee able to make me eate my worde. I knowe ſuch Courtes were appointed for the correction of vices,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:10166:67"/> but nowe they cheriſh vice, and correct vertue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>I ſee your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice doth breake out further and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: I will take notice of your words, and deſire thoſe which are preſent to remember them. You ſayde all is done for money, the Lawes are broken, and the Queenes ſubiectes abuſed. You add further, that they cheriſh vice and correct vertue. Theſe I tell you plain, be foule accuſations, and you accuſe all in generall, none excepted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>I did ſpeake gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, or rather indefinitely, but yet my meaning is not to include euery parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer perſon. But my meaning is, that for the moſt part the Courtes be ſuch: I doe not ſay all are ſuch, for I knowe not all. I truſt in God there bee ſome fewe that either are, or haue beene iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in ſuch Courtes, that doe feare the Lorde. My ſpeeche doth not accuſe them, hee that is cleare, is not to bee greeued: whereas you take ſuch notice of my words, I woulde I might before the cheefe in the land, vnder the pain of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:10166:68"/> ſharp puniſhment if I failed, bee dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to make proofe againſte the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Courtes, that all is done for Monie, that the lawes are broken, the Subiectes abuſed, vice cheriſhed, and vertue puniſhed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>If you dare bee ſo bolde to take vppon you, ſuch a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, you may let vs knowe ſomewhat nowe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>You ſeeme to bee ſuche a Straunger vnto the matter, that you knowe nothinge. I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile howe you ſhould bee ignoraunt in that which is ſo manifeſt and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantlie knowne, that the verie Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of ſuch courts which haue their liuing that waie, are afraid they ſhould bee accounted impudente, if they ſhoulde denie that monie beareth the ſwaie among them. Let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens tell what they paie for their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Billes, for Bookes of Articles: if the Booke be woorth two pence, the price muſt bee ſixe pence. What ſay you to the probates of Teſtamentes, what exceſſiue extortion is committed
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:10166:68"/> that waie? but of all other thinges, the greateſt gaine commeth in, when ſome welthy ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is in for adultry. For he wil come off ſomwhat roundlie, rather then ſtand in a white ſheete. If the matter be verie plaine and manifeſt: yet that the court maie ſeeme to deal honeſtlie, and hide the fauor which is ſhewed, he muſt haue his compingators: and then come in the vileſt men that can bee picked, ſuch as be the moſte notorious Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerds, and men paſt ſhame, and ſo he is quit by al his peeres. It hath falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better ſpeede, ſome that haue bene abſolued (being preſented for euil vices &amp; exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate) haue by &amp; by like good honeſt men bene ſworn to help out their neighbor. The Proctors for their fees take part on euery ſide, it is a very fowl clowt which they wil not help to waſh. The ſummoners they rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge abroad to driue into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> net: but their cheefe gaine is out of the Court: It is better to take a cheeze or a buſhell of wheate, then <hi>4.</hi> pence for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eſpecially whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their good maſters wil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fee. whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any miniſters are preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by churchwarde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:10166:69"/> for any groſe vices, that bill is nipt in the head, and buryed in the pocket of a gowne. Shall it be thought credible, that among all the Church-wardens and ſworne men in a ſhire, there bee not a number of that honeſty that they will not be periured? They muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſuch miniſters as do not catechiſe, ſuch as be Carders, Dicers, Alehouſe-hunters, ſuch as liue in ſuſpicion for incontinencie. What a rablement are there of theſe? And yet how manye of them haue beene puniſhed? There is no Godly Preacher, but doth loath this dealing, and that ſetteth theſe Courtes at deadly warre with him. They touze him, he is a diſobedient fellowe, he is worſe then dogges meat. The people which imbrace the Goſpell are much ſuſpected to beare ſmall liking vnto theſe Courts, And therefore, manye of them are cited, which haue Idoll mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters at hoame, and goe vnto other Townes to heare the worde preached. Syrah, you are a diſordered fellow, you breake the Queenes lawes, you do not keepe your parriſh Church. When an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:10166:69"/> is made, we haue no teaching at home, we goe to be taught. What is replyed, yee ſhall be made to tarry at home. But for this time, pay the Fees of the Court, which is ſixteene pence a man, and get yee hence. They anſwere, we are poore men, we haue wrong to be cited for this matter, we truſt yee will ſpare vs. If any do not pay his ſixteene pence, then there goeth out an excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication from the Scribe, vnder the name of the iudge. Lay theſe things to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, &amp; tell me whether mony do not beare the ſway, the Queenes ſubiectes be not abuſed, the lawes broken, vice cheriſhed, and vertue puniſhed. I haue hearde, that he which is preſented vnto a benefice, ſhould haue his inſtitution &amp; induction, for xvi. ſhillinges or there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout: And now it is grown to 3. pound if it be not more, vnder ſome Biſhops.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>I doe not know for mine owne part, whether it be ſo: but in deede it is a generall accuſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all men, that there is great cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in thoſe Courtes. It is great pitty, if it be ſo. But there is no calling
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:10166:70"/> nor office, in which there will not grow abuſes. We may not reiect a thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is abuſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philedon.</speaker>
               <p>How would ye haue men liue, if they maye not take their Fees. They y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> take paines muſt be paid for it. The officers are at no ſmal charges, for their meat and for their Horſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>No, no, theſe pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhe waiwarde men doe lie and ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and make thinges worſe then they bee. It is their maner to make great matters of nothing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>If you count this to lie and ſlaunder, what would you ſaie if all ſhould be tolde. I doubt not but as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde ſaith to <hi>Ezechiel, I will yet ſhew thee greater abhominations:</hi> So he which knoweth the ſecreats and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, in theſe Courtes might make men wonder, conſidering that all goeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name and title of the Goſpell. It can not be, but they will wax worſe and worſe, becauſe they bend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues againſt thoſe that be good, and are an arme vnto the wicked.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrematos.</speaker>
               <p>They bend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:10166:70" rendition="simple:additions"/> againſt none but diſordered per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that will not obeye lawes, thoſe you count good, but they may be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted rebels. Such as be honeſt &amp; quiet ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and like not of your waies, thoſe be the wicked whom you ſpeake of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>You ſpeake much of diſordered perſons, that will not obeye lawes, whom you terme rebels. If you wait vntill ſuch time as they make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, your eies will ſincke into your head. Where did you ſee that thoſe men (whom you terme Puritanes) did euer giue anie ſuſpicion of tumult or rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion? they haue learned, that they ought to ſpende their liues in defence of their Prince, and that it is damnation to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the powers which God hath ſet vp. <hi>Rom. 13.</hi> You al ſay they be but trifles which men ſticke at. And in words you wil ſeeme to wiſh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea. Are thoſe rebels which ſtag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger at ſome things which you confes be trifles &amp; might be ſpared? The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what wil yee account of Biſhops &amp; Archdeacons, which breake godly lawes, which be of ſubſtance? they ſeeme to be zealous for
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:10166:71"/> the defence and maintenance of lawes, but it is not ſo, for then would they not breake the lawes. They are afrayde, that euerye one which refuſeth to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to all that they would haue him, doth diſalow of the Hierarchie. They be afrayd that all Puritans do beleeue that onely our Lord Ieſus, and no mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man may haue the honour, to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Archipoymen</hi> or <hi>Archiepiſcopos</hi> prince of Paſtours, and prince of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, <hi>1. Pet. 5. ver. 4.</hi> They are afraid that theſe waiward Puritanes, take it vnmeet, that chriſt ſhold be in the ſhape of a ſeruant while he preached the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, &amp; his miniſters and officers ſhould be as Dukes, and Earles, and Barons, and the noble pieres of the world. <hi>Hinc illae lachrimae.</hi> This is the ſoare. From hence ariſeth all the warre. The thing is ſo manifeſt, that ſhortly they muſt lay aſide all pretence of the Goſpell, and of the peace of the Church, and ſay plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we fight for our owne eſtate. And I pray ye, let me go a little further. Was it euer ſeene, that all the filthie men of the worlde, and ſuch as are rotten in
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:10166:71"/> their ſinnes did take part with Chriſt, with his Apoſtles, or with the Godly which ſucceeded them? Will the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of Sathan ſeeke to vpholde the kingdome of Chriſt? Goe through the land, take a view, if yee find not this, let me looſe my life. Namely, that all the rancke adulterers, common drunkards, vnthrifts, ruffians, &amp; horrible ſwearers, deſpiſers of the worde of God, doe take part with the Biſhops, and cry downe with theſe rebell Puritans. Looke fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and yee ſhall finde that many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, which will be loath to heare a Sermon, do now beſtirre them, where there is any whom they terme a Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan Preacher, to enquire what matter he vttered, that he may bee complained of and put downe. Who carry the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaintes, but ſuch as haue loſt all ſhew of honeſtie? Theſe (although they bee neuer ſo full of all vngodlines) are now become the good ſubiectes. Theſe be honeſt and quiet men: well, I truſt the Lord Ieſus ſhall neuer need the ſeruice of ſuch. Who reioice ſo much nowe as the Papiſtes? They ſee the Preachers
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:10166:72"/> of the Goſpell withſtood, and defaced. They ſee that ſuch as haue laboured moſt diligently to inſtruct the people, and to drawe them from the errours of poperie, are accounted the worſt men, and ſooneſt put to ſilence. This maketh them alreadie verie crancke and to ſet vp their briſtles, and to ſpeake boldly. It is a common thing now, not in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but in the open ſtreates, ſounding in the eares of manie, theſe Goſpellers be rebels, theſe profeſſors be knaues, it were no matter if they were hanged.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philochrem.</speaker>
               <p>The Papiſts haue no cauſe to reioyce, nor to ſet vp their bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, becauſe the Puritans be defaced. They haue ſtrengthened the Papiſtes. You ſpeake of the preachers, the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, as thogh they were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onelie prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers. God be thanked, there be a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of learned Preachers beſides them: Other maner of men then they be. If they be as you ſaie thirtie or fortie in a ſhire, what is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to the whole number of learned men? And for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber you ſpeak of, I wiſſe, there be ſundry which are no great learned men, which neuer tooke
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:10166:72"/> degree in the ſchooles. The reſt might be better aduiſed, and ſhew them ſelues more dutifull ſubiects. You complaine of thoſe which take part with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Archdeacons againſt the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans; as namely that all deſpiſers of Gods word, adulterers, drunckards, ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fians, and vnthrifts, and other ſuch like: I praie ye are there not as great faults among the Puritans? Are not they full of hatred and malice?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodox.</speaker>
               <p>You ſeeme to make ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie light that thirtie or fortie preathers ſhoulde be put to ſilence in a ſhire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is but a ſmal number compared with the whol multitude of learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I know the number is ſmal in deede, in reſpect of the whol miniſtrie: but if you reſpect faithful &amp; diligent Teachers, it ſhalbe found a great number. Set a ſide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt part which be vnlearned, and come to ſuch as be learned. Firſt reckon vp the number of non reſidents &amp; duble beneficed men, which in deed are verie many. Some of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> attending about the Court, ſome in Biſhops houſes, ſome ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at London, ſome in the vniuerſities.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:10166:73"/> looke next vpon thoſe idle Preachers, which preach once in a quarter, or once in two moneths, and are more in the bowling alley then in their ſtudy. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, conſider what vnſkilfull men doe preach: yea, rather prophane the holy worde of God: and what vngodlie men there be of them: and in how great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber all theſe are, and you ſhall ſee a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, &amp; lamentable face of a Church, when thirty or forty, which taught dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently are taken away. I graunt there bee ſome which neuer tooke degree in ſchools, but yet can ſo handle the word, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſundry which are Doctors, may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, that they be not comparable to them. You know there be ſundry, whom you reproche with Puritaniſme, which haue taken the higheſt degree in the ſchooles. Many others alſo which haue taken the other degrees, and doe not go without the Doctorſhippe for want of learning. You woulde haue thoſe that profeſſe the Goſpell to be accounted as euill as the Drunkardes and Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers. You charge them with hatred and malice, no doubt it commeth to paſſe,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:10166:73"/> that among thoſe that profeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell there be hipocrites. For want of plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inſtruction, there be alſo ſundrie weake. But the hatred &amp; malice which you ſpeake of, is, that they will not bee partakers with vngodlie men in their euil waies, that cauſeth them to ſpeake ſo much of malice, and want of loue. For it ſeemeth the greateſt hatred in the world vnto carnall men, when any miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like their waies. This is it which <hi>Saint Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of, in the fourth chapiter of his firſte Epiſtle, which I alſo cited before. <hi>Wherein</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it ſeemeth to them ſtraunge, that yee runne not with them vnto the ſame exceſſe of riote, therefore ſpeake they euill of you.</hi> He is blind y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeeth not this plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully fulfilled in our time. You ſaie, they might ſhew them ſelues more dutifull ſubiectes. It falleth out ſomtimes, that thoſe which are the worſt ſubiectes, and ſuch as do Princes verie great hurt, doe accuſe thoſe to be euill ſubiectes, which of all other are the moſt faithfull. Did not <hi>Abner</hi> and other of King <hi>Saules</hi> Councellers, take them ſelues to be his
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:10166:74"/> beſt ſubiects? and yet who led him from God vnto his deſtruction but they, by ſtirring him vp to perſecute <hi>Dauid?</hi> Did they not accuſe <hi>Dauid</hi> to be a trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, &amp; yet who was ſo faithful and true harted vnto his Lord as he? Wiſe men muſt not be carried away with a blaſt of wordes, nor with ſome colour of matter which vngodly men neuer want againſt the good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philocrhematos.</speaker>
               <p>I perceiue it is but in vaine to ſpende the time in talking with ſuch as you, which are obſtinately &amp; wilfullie bent. You will be ſinguler.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>Obſtinacie and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes can not be, but in an vngodly and naughtie matter. For a man can not be too ſtedfaſt in the truth. Let the cauſe be good, and the more ſtiffe and conſtant the minde is, ſo much the better. If I haue vttered or defend anie falſhood, let me be conuicted, and I will yeeld. If I be not conuicted, what reaſon is there that I ſhoulde be charged with wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes or obſtinacie? If Ieſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles be of my ſide, what wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes is it to ſay I would be ſinguler?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:10166:74"/>
               <speaker>Philodox.</speaker>
               <p>It were well if yee would all agree, &amp; teach vs that be of the laiety by your good example, for that ought to be in yee. And how ſhal it be expected at our hands to liue in vnitie, &amp; to do well, when thoſe are at diſcord and variaunce which ſhould inſtruct and guid vs? Can yee exhort vs vnto concorde, and your ſelues at variance?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodox.</speaker>
               <p>You ſpeak of that which was neuer ſeene in this world, nor neuer ſhall. For ſo long as God hath faithfull meſſengers, ſo long will alſo the Deuill haue his vngodly inſtrumentes. Theſe can neuer agree, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one part ſeruing god, &amp; the other liuing viciouſly. And I pray yee, how or wherin wold yee haue them to agree? Which part ſhall condeſcend vnto the other? Which part ſhal yeeld? Shall thoſe that holde the truth giue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer? That is abhominable to bee ſpoken and ſhall neuer be. Will thoſe that are vngodlie yeelde &amp; ſubmit them ſelues vnto the truth? No, their ſtomach will not let them, though they be conuict in conſcience. Moreouer, this is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that ſuch a man as is not ſanctified,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:10166:75"/> but delighteth in worldly luſtes, cannot abide the puritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word, which doth condemne him. Herein the world is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious, that they crie out for vnitie, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, blaming alwaies that part which holdeth the truth, becauſe they woulde haue them yeelde vnto their affections, ſeeing they cannot abide to forſake their vild luſtes. Againe, a number of yee bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouercome of your carnall luſtes, are glad to make this pretence and excuſe. We cannot tell what to do. The Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers cannot agree, they be all naught, what ſhold we giue heede to follow any thing which they teach? theſe be helliſh and brutiſh ſpeeches. Yee muſt ſeeke out which hold the truth, which call yee vnto true godlines, and amendement of life, and with them yee muſt be at vnity. The true Preachers are not to exhort men to be at ſuch an vnitie as you ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine. But they muſt teach them to flie the fellowſhip of the wicked. I woulde to God men woulde conſider this, and tourne vnto him, and not like Giants fight againſt him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>I do not thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> anie
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:10166:75"/> do fight againſt God: You ſhoulde not vtter anie ſuch ſpeeche vnleſſe yee did know it to be true: a man can not fight againſt God, vnleſſe hee hate God, and I dare not iudge ſo euill of anie man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodoxos.</speaker>
               <p>You think none fight againſt God, becauſe whomſoeuer a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fighteth againſt, him he hateth and you dare not iudge ſo euil of anie man, to be ſo fowlie giuen ouer, as to hate God. It is groſe ignorance in ye, which ſeemeth to be excellent modeſtie: For if you had eies y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> could diſcern, you ſhould ſee how horriblie ſome men doe hate the Lorde God, and deſperatlie fight againſt him. Moſte true it is, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked men are ſo blinded, by a iuſt iudgment of God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they think they loue God, or at leaſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do not hate him: But we maie not iudge according to the ſence of fleſh &amp; bloud, but according to the ſacred truth of holie ſcripture: by which I wil make the matter plaine vnto yee. The bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Rom. 8.</hi> doth affirme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>ſuch as walke after the fleſh ſhall dye.</hi> He rendreth a reaſon, which is, <hi>that the wiſdom of the fleſh, is enimity againſt
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:10166:76"/> God?</hi> And whie is it enimitie againſt God? or whie doth the holy ghoſt charge it to leaue hatred againſt him? becauſe (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>It is not ſubiect to the law of God: neither in deede can bee.</hi> Marke this well, for it is euen as a thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derbolt, wherby al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked are ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken down: they bear themſelues in hand y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they loue God, they make open brags and vaunts, that they be his friendes: but you maie learn heere fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mouth of the Lorde him ſelfe, that whoſoeuer are not Subiect to the obedience of his law, they bee his enimies and doe hate him. Then doth it follow, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whoſoeuer do fight againſt his word, or anie parte thereof, they are his enimies, they doe hate him &amp; fight againſt him. Then let vs come to the matter. Is there anie reaſonable man but will confeſſe, that Gods worde doth commaund learned &amp; godlie miniſters, to teach and guid his people? Doth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture laie woes and curſes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be contrarie? Is it not his holie ordinance y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euerie ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard ſhall attend vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flock of which he hath taken the charge and ouerſight?
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:10166:76"/> Do not thoſe then monſtrouſlie fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and hate him, which in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, in their bookes publiſhed abroad, do with reaſons drawne from the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſh, defend non reſidentes, double beneficed men, &amp; the vnlearned miniſtery, with ſundrie abominations? The dreadfull vengeance of God doth hang ouer the heads of ſuch men, vnleſſe they repent in time. They doe againſt their Conſcience, for they can not but know ſuch things as be euill. The loue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world doth carrie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto it. God hath alſo commaunded that his meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ſhall be well intertained, that his Church maie be built. Do they not then directly fight againſt him, which deface &amp; moleſt them, depriuing multitudes of people of the foode of theire ſoules: This is yet a more ſhameleſſe matter, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euen ſuch as be old turncoats, &amp; it is to be feared, readie to ſaie Maſſe again, are great inſtrumentes. Such beeing known athieſts, are not aſhamed to ſtep into the Pulpit &amp; to charge the Godlie &amp; faithfull meſſengers of the Lorde, to be Atheiſts, rebells, traitors, &amp; I know
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:10166:77"/> not what. If the cauſe bee good, let not ſuch guiltie perſons defend it, take ſuch as be not ſpotted: Shall thoſe ſtand as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> champions in the Lords battell, which haue imbraced this preſent worlde, and ſeeke after gaine? Theſe fight for their bellie, &amp; not for the Lord. Thoſe whom the people calleth greedie Dogs, could not be more greedie then theſe: for they be neuer ſatiſfied. The Lord giue them repentance or elſe diſburden his church of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philedonos.</speaker>
               <p>I am ſorie there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſuch taſke in my houſe: If you will go to your chambers all things are readie, the Night is well ſpent.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10166:77"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
